[
  {
    "questionNum": 74001,
    "questionText": " When is the Commonwealth Day observed by its member countries?",
    "answerText": " 24-May-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74002,
    "questionText": " During whose viceroyalty was the system of Budget introduced in India?",
    "answerText": " Canning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74003,
    "questionText": " A soap bubble is given negative charge then what happen in its radius?",
    "answerText": " Increases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74004,
    "questionText": " When an ebonite rod is rubbed with fur; which charge acquired by the fur?",
    "answerText": " Positive"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74005,
    "questionText": " The most important feature in the economic measures pursued by Alauddin Khalji what was that?",
    "answerText": " Market control"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74006,
    "questionText": " Which is the only golfer to win the Masters Tournament six times?",
    "answerText": " Jack Nicklaus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74007,
    "questionText": " How is the pitch of the voice of women generally?",
    "answerText": " Higher than that of men"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74008,
    "questionText": " What was the original name of Swami Dayananda Saraswati?",
    "answerText": " Mula Shankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74009,
    "questionText": " Where did the Indian National Army (I.N.A.) come into existence?",
    "answerText": " Singapore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74010,
    "questionText": " Heating pyrites in air to remove sulphur is known as which name?",
    "answerText": " Roasting"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74011,
    "questionText": " When is International Day of Peace; recognized by the UN is observed?",
    "answerText": " 21-Sep-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74012,
    "questionText": " A Municipal Corporation is set up in a city with how much population of not less than?",
    "answerText": " 10 lakh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74013,
    "questionText": " Which tree require highest amount of water for growth?",
    "answerText": " Euclyptus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74014,
    "questionText": " Which type of forest belt supplies most of the world’s requirement of newsprint?",
    "answerText": " Coniferous forest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74015,
    "questionText": " Which instrument instrument used for recording earthquake waves?",
    "answerText": " Seismograph"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74016,
    "questionText": " Who has written the book ‘My Frozen Turbulence in Kashmir’?",
    "answerText": " Jagmohan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74017,
    "questionText": " What is the mixture of carbon monoxide and hydrogen called?",
    "answerText": " Water gas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74018,
    "questionText": " Ogaden region has been a source of conflict between which countries?",
    "answerText": " Ethiopia and Somalia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74019,
    "questionText": " Who was the only Governor-General/Viceroy to be assassinated in India?",
    "answerText": " Lord Mayo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74020,
    "questionText": " Which Indian leader was dismissed by British from the Indian Civil Service?",
    "answerText": " Surendranath Banerji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74021,
    "questionText": " What does Every object at a temperature above absolute zero?",
    "answerText": " Radiates energy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74022,
    "questionText": " Which river is known as ‘Vridha Ganga’?",
    "answerText": " Godavari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74023,
    "questionText": " Who is considered to be the father of Ayurveda?",
    "answerText": " Charaka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74024,
    "questionText": " The latitude of a place expresses its angular position relative to which line?",
    "answerText": " Equator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74025,
    "questionText": " Nobel Laureate Muhammed Yunus belongs to which country?",
    "answerText": " Bangladesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74026,
    "questionText": " With which sport is Leroy Burrell associated?",
    "answerText": " Athletics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74027,
    "questionText": " In which year were Private Sector Mutual Funds in India permitted?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74028,
    "questionText": " Which natural region is not found in the Torrid Zone?",
    "answerText": " Temperate deserts"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74029,
    "questionText": " Who; was the Nanda ruler at the time of Alexander's invasion?",
    "answerText": " Dhana Nanda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74030,
    "questionText": " Which Sultan of Delhi introduced measures for improving the quality of fruits?",
    "answerText": " Firoz shah Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74031,
    "questionText": " What does not affect visibility on the ground?",
    "answerText": " Dew"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74032,
    "questionText": " Which is the only woman to have won three Wimbledon titles in a row?",
    "answerText": " Steffi Graff"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74033,
    "questionText": " Why is In a hydel station the motion produced in turbines?",
    "answerText": " Due to the flow of water"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74034,
    "questionText": " The famous Petronas Twin Towers are located in which country?",
    "answerText": " Malaysia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74035,
    "questionText": " What does the Preamble of our Constitution contain?",
    "answerText": " The spirit of the Constitution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74036,
    "questionText": " The Matatila multipurpose project is located in which state?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74037,
    "questionText": " What the twelve constellations to as zodiac?",
    "answerText": " A group of stars"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74038,
    "questionText": " Who was named India’s Cricketer of the Century by Wisden?",
    "answerText": " Kapil Dev"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74039,
    "questionText": " In the Semi-arid and Temperate grasslands; which are the most commonly found animals?",
    "answerText": " Sheep and goats1"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74040,
    "questionText": " Which sea is without a coasts?",
    "answerText": " Sargasso sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74041,
    "questionText": " In which city was Galileo born?",
    "answerText": " Pisa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74042,
    "questionText": " Which year is celebrated as International Year of the Shark?",
    "answerText": 2009
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74043,
    "questionText": " Dr. Hargobing khurana received the nobel prize for which subject?",
    "answerText": " Medicine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74044,
    "questionText": " Sufi Kalam; a type of devotional music; is the characteristic of which state?",
    "answerText": " Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74045,
    "questionText": " Which country is rich in oil?",
    "answerText": " Indonesia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74046,
    "questionText": " What is Funny Bone?",
    "answerText": " A nerve"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74047,
    "questionText": " What is the most abundant element on the earth’s crust by weight?",
    "answerText": " Oxygen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74048,
    "questionText": " Which body finalises the Five Year Plan proposals?",
    "answerText": " National Development Council"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74049,
    "questionText": " Which language is not recognised in the 8th Schedule though it is an official language of a State?",
    "answerText": " English"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74050,
    "questionText": " Mangrane vegetation in India is most extensive in which forest?",
    "answerText": " Sunder bans"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74051,
    "questionText": " Who wrote the book Babubivah?",
    "answerText": " Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74052,
    "questionText": " Thermal decomposition of alkanes is known as which name?",
    "answerText": " Cracking"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74053,
    "questionText": " Which substance is used to retard the setting action of cement?",
    "answerText": " CaSO.2HO"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74054,
    "questionText": " Which is the chief characteristic of wet and dry tropics?",
    "answerText": " Constant heating"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74055,
    "questionText": " Which waves are used for a communication through artificial satellites?",
    "answerText": " Microwaves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74056,
    "questionText": " Iris has no pigment in which people?",
    "answerText": " Blue-eyed people"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74057,
    "questionText": " From the Earth to the sun is one AU what does AU stand for?",
    "answerText": " Astronomical Unit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74058,
    "questionText": " In which part of the eye lies the pigment; that decides the colour of the eyes of a person?",
    "answerText": " Choroid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74059,
    "questionText": " Which would be most suited for an area which has only two months of scanty rainfall in a year?",
    "answerText": " Pulse"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74060,
    "questionText": " How were the ritualistic precepts attached to the hymns of the Vedas known?",
    "answerText": " Brahmanas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74061,
    "questionText": " From the evolutionary point of view; which is closer to man?",
    "answerText": " Dolphin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74062,
    "questionText": " Which was the Russian scientist who proposed the theory of origin of life?",
    "answerText": " Oparin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74063,
    "questionText": " What is the name of scale meant for recording weather condition?",
    "answerText": " Fahrenheit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74064,
    "questionText": " What was the capital of Kakatiya dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Warangal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74065,
    "questionText": " Among the SAARC country; which is the most densely populated country?",
    "answerText": " Bangladesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74066,
    "questionText": " When Alexander invaded India; who were the rulers of Magadha?",
    "answerText": " Nandas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74067,
    "questionText": " Which is the most populous city in the world?",
    "answerText": " Tokyo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74068,
    "questionText": " The Winter Olympic came into being in which year?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74069,
    "questionText": " In which is ‘Foot and Mouth Disease’ found?",
    "answerText": " Cattle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74070,
    "questionText": " For how many years is rolling plan?",
    "answerText": " One year"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74071,
    "questionText": " Through which material does sound travel slowest?",
    "answerText": " Wood"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74072,
    "questionText": " A convex mirror makes a good rear-view mirror for a car. Why?",
    "answerText": " It forms erect; reduced images"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74073,
    "questionText": " In India; who was the first to put forward the theory that the earth revolves round the sun?",
    "answerText": " Aryabhatta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74074,
    "questionText": " When did Unrepresented- Nations and Peoples Organisation come into existence?",
    "answerText": 1991
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74075,
    "questionText": " What was the source of the blue gem stone; lapis lazuli; for the people of Harappan culture?",
    "answerText": " Afghanistan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74076,
    "questionText": " The first explosion of an atomic device in India was carried out in which state?",
    "answerText": " Rajasthan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74077,
    "questionText": " What is Study of growth and development of embryo?",
    "answerText": " Embryology"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74078,
    "questionText": " What is the total surface area of earth?",
    "answerText": " 510 million sq km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74079,
    "questionText": " Which is the type of movement that occurs during opening and closing of flower?",
    "answerText": " Nastic movement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74080,
    "questionText": " Which feature is the product of vulcancity?",
    "answerText": " Atoll"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74081,
    "questionText": " Who is the highest Law Officer of a State?",
    "answerText": " Advocate General"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74082,
    "questionText": " Why is fog common around Newfoundland coast?",
    "answerText": " Because warm and cold currents meet"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74083,
    "questionText": " Buddha died in which Mahajanpada?",
    "answerText": " Mall"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74084,
    "questionText": " Before ascending the Maurya throne; How was Ashoka served?",
    "answerText": " As a Viceroy of Taxila"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74085,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Operation Blackboard?",
    "answerText": " Promoting adult literacy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74086,
    "questionText": " Tipu Sultan died fighting the English forces under which general?",
    "answerText": " Lord Cornwallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74087,
    "questionText": " Which chemically inactive gas present in the atmosphere?",
    "answerText": " Argon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74088,
    "questionText": " When was petroleum discovered first in commercial quantitie in India?",
    "answerText": 1890
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74089,
    "questionText": " Why is the yellow colour of urine?",
    "answerText": " Due to the presence of urochrome"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74090,
    "questionText": " After respiration the conversion of energy is mainly in which form of?",
    "answerText": " ATP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74091,
    "questionText": " What is the most abundant on the earth crust?",
    "answerText": " Aluminium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74092,
    "questionText": " The first Commonwealth Games were held in the year 1930 at which place?",
    "answerText": " Hamilton (Canade)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74093,
    "questionText": " ORT (Oral Rehydration Therapy) is associated with the treatment of which disease?",
    "answerText": " Diarrhea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74094,
    "questionText": " What is the mean of ‘Take off stage’ in an economy?",
    "answerText": " Steady growth begins"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74095,
    "questionText": " Who is directly responsible to Parliament for all matters concerning the Defence Services of India?",
    "answerText": " Defence Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74096,
    "questionText": " In vulcanisation; with which the natural rubber is heated?",
    "answerText": " Sulphur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74097,
    "questionText": " Which human rights organisation founded 1961 got Nobel 1977?",
    "answerText": " Amnesty International"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74098,
    "questionText": " Where is the largest automobile manufacturing centre in the world located?",
    "answerText": " Detroit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74099,
    "questionText": " Sodium metal is kept under which liquid?",
    "answerText": " Kerosene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74100,
    "questionText": " Under whose guidance was the Congress policy of pray and petition ultimately come to an end?",
    "answerText": " Lala Lajpat Rai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74101,
    "questionText": " What was the name of the learned lady who is said to have debated with the famous law-giver Yajnavalkya?",
    "answerText": " Gargi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74102,
    "questionText": " The river Cauvery originates from which state?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74103,
    "questionText": " A person returning from abroad can retain foreign currency up to what period?",
    "answerText": " 90 days"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74104,
    "questionText": " If the dew point is below freezing; it is referred to which point?",
    "answerText": " Frost point"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74105,
    "questionText": " At the beginning of the twentieth century; who published ‘The Economic: History of India’?",
    "answerText": " Romesh Chandra Dutt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74106,
    "questionText": " Which rays will deflect in electric field?",
    "answerText": " Cathode rays"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74107,
    "questionText": " How are Air-pockets that cause aircrafts to lose altitude suddenly caused?",
    "answerText": " Temperature inversions"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74108,
    "questionText": " Where did India made her debut in Olympic football?",
    "answerText": " London in 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74109,
    "questionText": " Which characteristic is common among parrot; platypus and kangaroo?",
    "answerText": " Functional post anal tail"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74110,
    "questionText": " Which vitamin is essential for the coagulation of blood?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin K"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74111,
    "questionText": " ഓയിൽ ഒഫ് വിട്രിയോൾ എന്നറിയപ്പെടുന്നത്? ",
    "answerText": " സൾഫ്യൂരിക് ആസിഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74112,
    "questionText": " How is Indian economy?",
    "answerText": " Mixed economy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74113,
    "questionText": " By when is extinction of a species in a food chain compensated?",
    "answerText": " Food web"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74114,
    "questionText": " What is the most suitable unit for expressing nuclear radius?",
    "answerText": " Fermi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74115,
    "questionText": " ‘Ashes’ is the term associated with which sport?",
    "answerText": " Football"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74116,
    "questionText": " What was the primary purpose of a seal in the Indus Valley Civilisation?",
    "answerText": " To signify ownership of property"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74117,
    "questionText": " Of which dried flower buds are used as a spice?",
    "answerText": " Cloves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74118,
    "questionText": " Lahnaphophobia is the fear of what?",
    "answerText": " Vegetables"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74119,
    "questionText": " Which Sultan had greatest number of slaves in his court?",
    "answerText": " Firoz shah Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74120,
    "questionText": " In which state is Jog Falls located?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74121,
    "questionText": " Which type of woods is specially used as railways sleepers?",
    "answerText": " Jarrah and barri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74122,
    "questionText": " Famous book ‘The Return of the Native’ is written by which author?",
    "answerText": " Thomos Hardy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74123,
    "questionText": " Wilma Rudolf first black US woman to win Olympic gold where?",
    "answerText": " Rome in 1960"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74124,
    "questionText": " From which date shall the tenure of every Panchayat be for five years?",
    "answerText": " From the date of its first meeting"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74125,
    "questionText": " Whose nickname was the Cholisa or the Group of Forty?",
    "answerText": " Turkish nobility created by Iltutmish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74126,
    "questionText": " Which part of human brain is most highly developed as compared to others?",
    "answerText": " Cerebrum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74127,
    "questionText": " Who in ancient India assumed the title amitraghata?",
    "answerText": " Bindusar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74128,
    "questionText": " What is the approximate circumference of the Earth?",
    "answerText": " 30;000 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74129,
    "questionText": " On which date India became a Sovereign; democratic republic?",
    "answerText": " Jan 26; 1950"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74130,
    "questionText": " What is the vertical component of earth’s magnetic field?",
    "answerText": 0
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74131,
    "questionText": " Which act made the Indian Legislature bicameral?",
    "answerText": " Government of India Act; 1919"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74132,
    "questionText": " Which plant is preferred for mixed cropping in order to enhance the bioavailability of nitrogen?",
    "answerText": " Gram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74133,
    "questionText": " Which gland is both exo and endocrine gland?",
    "answerText": " Pancreas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74134,
    "questionText": " Thick stems and thorny wax coated leaves are commonly found in which area?",
    "answerText": " Deserts"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74135,
    "questionText": " What is a mixture of potassium nitrate; powdered charcoal and sulphur called?",
    "answerText": " Gun powder"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74136,
    "questionText": " Which Sultan of Delhi; declared himself as a lieutenant of Caliph?",
    "answerText": " Iltutmish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74137,
    "questionText": " In which year was the first Indian Councils Act passed?",
    "answerText": 1861
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74138,
    "questionText": " Which gas is used for refrigeration?",
    "answerText": " Ammonia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74139,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Gulliver’s Travels?",
    "answerText": " Jonathon Swift"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74140,
    "questionText": " Which region is culturally closer to India but ethnically closer to China?",
    "answerText": " South-East Asia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74141,
    "questionText": " What is Anosmia?",
    "answerText": " Loss of the sense of smell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74142,
    "questionText": " The autobiography ‘Living History’ has been authored by author?",
    "answerText": " Hillary Clinton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74143,
    "questionText": " Who was the Afghan ruler of India whose administrative system was emulated by the British?",
    "answerText": " Sher Shah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74144,
    "questionText": " In Japan what colour car is reserved for the royal family only?",
    "answerText": " Maroon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74145,
    "questionText": " Where is the Central Water and Power Research Station located?",
    "answerText": " Khadakwasla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74146,
    "questionText": " Which is known as master gland in man?",
    "answerText": " Pituitary"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74147,
    "questionText": " Which purified oil does Aviation fuel for jet aeroplanes consist?",
    "answerText": " Kerosene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74148,
    "questionText": " Which gland in human body is popularly called ‘Adam’s apple’?",
    "answerText": " Thyroid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74149,
    "questionText": " Where has the world’s largest monolithic statue of Buddha been installed?",
    "answerText": " Bamiyan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74150,
    "questionText": " How much does the earth revolves round the sun in its orbit by approximately?",
    "answerText": " 1° per day"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74151,
    "questionText": " Whose autobiography was The long walk to Freedom?",
    "answerText": " Nelson Mandela"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74152,
    "questionText": " Upon which development the Second Five Year Plan laid mote stress?",
    "answerText": " Industrialisation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74153,
    "questionText": " Which Chola ruler converted the Bay of Bengal into a ‘Chela lake’?",
    "answerText": " Rajendra I"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74154,
    "questionText": " What is the duration of a basketball match both before and after the break?",
    "answerText": " 25 minutes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74155,
    "questionText": " Which genetic disease is sex -linked?",
    "answerText": " Royal haemophilia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74156,
    "questionText": " Which region is the world’s best cod-fishing ground?",
    "answerText": " North-east Atlantic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74157,
    "questionText": " Which country celebrates Christmas festival in summer season?",
    "answerText": " Australia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74158,
    "questionText": " Speed Post was started in?",
    "answerText": 1986
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74159,
    "questionText": " When some detergent is added to water; what will be the surface tension?",
    "answerText": " Increases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74160,
    "questionText": " During which reign was the Purana Qila constructed?",
    "answerText": " Sher Shah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74161,
    "questionText": " Where is the The headquarter of World Trade Organisation?",
    "answerText": " Geneva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74162,
    "questionText": " What is involved in controlling blood sugar level?",
    "answerText": " Islets of langerhans"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74163,
    "questionText": " When did India join the United Nations?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74164,
    "questionText": " Who ruler was the builder of Jahan-Panah; Delhi's fourth city?",
    "answerText": " Sultan Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74165,
    "questionText": " Evergreen oak forests are found at the height between how many meters?",
    "answerText": " 2700 and 4000 metres"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74166,
    "questionText": " Where is the thermal equator found?",
    "answerText": " North of geographical equator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74167,
    "questionText": " Which is another name of RDX?",
    "answerText": " Cycionite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74168,
    "questionText": " Which state leads in the production of maize?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74169,
    "questionText": " What is a physical basis of life?",
    "answerText": " Protoplasm"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74170,
    "questionText": " The tide at its maximum height is known by which name?",
    "answerText": " Spring tide"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74171,
    "questionText": " Which is the smallest country in South America?",
    "answerText": " Surinam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74172,
    "questionText": " Respiration can occur in the absence of oxygen in which thing?",
    "answerText": " Yeast"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74173,
    "questionText": " Which part of cockroach bears exo and endoskeleton?",
    "answerText": " Head"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74174,
    "questionText": " What was the main characteristic of the Indus Valley Civilization?",
    "answerText": " Town planning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74175,
    "questionText": " Which queen enjoyed political power along ‘with her husband?",
    "answerText": " Nur Jahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74176,
    "questionText": " Gum Kelucharan Mohapatra is a maestro of which dance form?",
    "answerText": " Kathak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74177,
    "questionText": " What is the approximate diameter of the earth?",
    "answerText": " 12;800 Km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74178,
    "questionText": " The term ‘deuce’ is common in which two games?",
    "answerText": " Badminton and Tennis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74179,
    "questionText": " If it is 4 P.M. on Monday at 150°W; what will be the time at 150°E?",
    "answerText": " Noon on Tuesday"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74180,
    "questionText": " Which was the The most important industry in Sangam age?",
    "answerText": " Production of cloth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74181,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of Pan American Health Organisation?",
    "answerText": " Mexico"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74182,
    "questionText": " Ultimate environmental hazard to mankind; why?",
    "answerText": " Due to Nuclear pollution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74183,
    "questionText": " By whom was the practice of Sati was declared illegal?",
    "answerText": " Lord William Bentinck"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74184,
    "questionText": " What is considered as the drug of last resort for human being?",
    "answerText": " Chloramphenical"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74185,
    "questionText": " Which is natural source of gamma-rays?",
    "answerText": " Radon gas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74186,
    "questionText": " Which Mughalemperor gave land for the construction of the Golden Temple at Amritsar?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74187,
    "questionText": " Which animal lays eggs?",
    "answerText": " Duck billed platypus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74188,
    "questionText": " In which state is Ranganathittu Bird Sanctuary located?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74189,
    "questionText": " Which common devices works on the basis of the principle of mutual induction?",
    "answerText": " Transformer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74190,
    "questionText": " Which is the example of ideal black body?",
    "answerText": " A pin hole box"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74191,
    "questionText": " When is International Holocaust Remembrance Day; recognized by the UN observed?",
    "answerText": " 27-Jan-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74192,
    "questionText": " Which lady wrote a historical account during the Mughal Period?",
    "answerText": " Gulbadan Begam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74193,
    "questionText": " In which year ‘Human Rights Resolution’ was adopted by the U.N.?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74194,
    "questionText": " Which was common both to the Harappan society and the Rigvedic society?",
    "answerText": " Horses"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74195,
    "questionText": " Most of hydrocarbons from petroleum are obtained by which method?",
    "answerText": " Fractional distillation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74196,
    "questionText": " To meet the growing needs for coins in the country; where does the Government propose to set up another mint?",
    "answerText": " Noida"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74197,
    "questionText": " With which game in Christianio Ronaldo associated?",
    "answerText": " Football"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74198,
    "questionText": " What is the most important factor in thunderstorms development?",
    "answerText": " Atmospheric instability"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74199,
    "questionText": " By whom was the most accepted theory for ascent of sap was given?",
    "answerText": " Dixon and Joly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74200,
    "questionText": " What is the normal temperature of human body on the kelvin scale?",
    "answerText": 310
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74201,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Muslim ruler to formulate the theory of Kingship similar to the theory of divine right of King?",
    "answerText": " Balban"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74202,
    "questionText": " Who established the earliest Surat factories?",
    "answerText": " English"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74203,
    "questionText": " By whom was Decimal system introduced?",
    "answerText": " Bhaskara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74204,
    "questionText": " In Finland who rides a goat named Ukko?",
    "answerText": " Santa Clause"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74205,
    "questionText": " The Tibetan river ‘Tsangpo’ enters India through which State?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74206,
    "questionText": " Who was the member of the Rajya Sabha when first appointed as the Prime Minister of India?",
    "answerText": " Indira Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74207,
    "questionText": " Who deserves the credit for the construction of Lal Quila at Agra?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74208,
    "questionText": " Which metal causes Itai-itai disease?",
    "answerText": " Cadmium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74209,
    "questionText": " Which has proved the best source of information for depicting India's ancient history?",
    "answerText": " Inscriptions"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74210,
    "questionText": " Who is the Patron Saint of boy scouts?",
    "answerText": " Saint George"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74211,
    "questionText": " Rainfall in the doldrums is of the nature of which precipitation?",
    "answerText": " Orographic precipitation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74212,
    "questionText": " In the kingdom of Satavahanas of ancient India; what was a district called?",
    "answerText": " Ahara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74213,
    "questionText": " Which part modified into pitcher in pitcher plant?",
    "answerText": " Leaf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74214,
    "questionText": " When it is noon along 82° 30’ longitude; along what degree of longitude it will be 30 a.m.?",
    "answerText": " 0°E or W"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74215,
    "questionText": " Which leader lives in the Potola?",
    "answerText": " Dalai Lama"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74216,
    "questionText": " From which rocks is the soil material mainly derived?",
    "answerText": " Sedimentary rocks"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74217,
    "questionText": " In plant body; by which the water and minerals are transported?",
    "answerText": " Xylum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74218,
    "questionText": " The term ‘double fault’ is associated with which game?",
    "answerText": " Tennis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74219,
    "questionText": " Lotteries organised by the government of a State come under which list?",
    "answerText": " State List"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74220,
    "questionText": " Who was known as the ‘Liberator of the Press’?",
    "answerText": " Metcalfe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74221,
    "questionText": " Who has written the book ‘The Famished Road’?",
    "answerText": " Ben Okri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74222,
    "questionText": " Which was the first talkie film of India?",
    "answerText": " Alam Ara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74223,
    "questionText": " Who was not a contemporary of the 'Other three?",
    "answerText": " Milinda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74224,
    "questionText": " Which is the richest source of ascorbic acid?",
    "answerText": " Guava"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74225,
    "questionText": " Rotation of the earth causes deflection of wind by which force?",
    "answerText": " Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74226,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest importer country of Indian textile?",
    "answerText": " USA"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74227,
    "questionText": " In which two sects was Jainism divided into?",
    "answerText": " Svetambara and Digambara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74228,
    "questionText": " The Ninth Schedule was added by which Amendment?",
    "answerText": " First"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74229,
    "questionText": " How long did the Constituent Assembly take to finally pass the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " About 3 years since Dec 9; 1946"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74230,
    "questionText": " Which is the second most abundant metal in the earth’s crust?",
    "answerText": " Aluminium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74231,
    "questionText": " What are the total members of Security Council–?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74232,
    "questionText": " What is the life of Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Permanency"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74233,
    "questionText": " The Indian research station Himadri is located at which place?",
    "answerText": " Antarctica"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74234,
    "questionText": " Which State was first annexed by Lord Dalhousie under the Doctrine of Lapse?",
    "answerText": " Satara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74235,
    "questionText": " Who was the earliest Sufi Saint to have settled at Ajmer?",
    "answerText": " Sheikh Moinuddin Chisti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74236,
    "questionText": " At absolute zero temperature; what will be the kinetic energy of the molecules?",
    "answerText": " Zero"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74237,
    "questionText": " The theory of use and disuse was used to explain evolution by which scientist?",
    "answerText": " Lamarck"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74238,
    "questionText": " By whom is the Annual Financial Statement caused to be laid before both Houses of Parliament?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74239,
    "questionText": " Why do the tropical cyclones not occur close to the equator?",
    "answerText": " Weak coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74240,
    "questionText": " Who wrote the Kalpasutra?",
    "answerText": " Bhadrabahu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74241,
    "questionText": " Which is not a sedimentary rock?",
    "answerText": " Marble"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74242,
    "questionText": " During which prime minister was the strategy of Rolling plan was adopted?",
    "answerText": " Morarji Desai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74243,
    "questionText": " If the temperature of a semiconductor rises; what is its resistivity?",
    "answerText": " Decrease"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74244,
    "questionText": " A body has a mass of kg on the Earth; when measured on the Moon; what would be its mas?",
    "answerText": " 6 kg"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74245,
    "questionText": " In Which year were the first Winter Olympic Games held?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74246,
    "questionText": " Which can come across if one travels through the Strait of Malacca?",
    "answerText": " Singapore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74247,
    "questionText": " Which dynasty succeeded Sungas?",
    "answerText": " Kanvas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74248,
    "questionText": " Absorption of water by root occurs in the region of which parts?",
    "answerText": " Root hairs"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74249,
    "questionText": " Which is the phase that invades but does not destroy the lost?",
    "answerText": " Temperate phase"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74250,
    "questionText": " What dose not contain a hydrophobic structure?",
    "answerText": " Rubber"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74251,
    "questionText": " In which part of the Constitution the concept of Welfare State finds elaboration?",
    "answerText": " Directive Principles"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74252,
    "questionText": " When iron rusts; how is its weight?",
    "answerText": " Increases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74253,
    "questionText": " In how many time zones has the world been divided into?",
    "answerText": 24
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74254,
    "questionText": " Where did the 1st ODI match was played in India?",
    "answerText": " Ahmedabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74255,
    "questionText": " In India; the concept of single citizenship is adopted from which country?",
    "answerText": " England"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74256,
    "questionText": " Where are the Local thunderstorms ‘Nor’ westers’ prominent?",
    "answerText": " West Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74257,
    "questionText": " Pulitzer prize is awarded for outstanding work in which field?",
    "answerText": " Literature and Journalism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74258,
    "questionText": " Which is the oldest atomic power station?",
    "answerText": " Tarapur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74259,
    "questionText": " In human beings; What is the opening of the stomach into the small Intestine called?",
    "answerText": " Pylorus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74260,
    "questionText": " Who was founder of Boy Scouts and Civil Guides Movement in India?",
    "answerText": " Baden Powell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74261,
    "questionText": " Which force is responsible for syncline formation?",
    "answerText": " Crustal compression"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74262,
    "questionText": " Who opposed Mahatma Gandhi’s association with the Khilafat movement?",
    "answerText": " Mohammed Alix Jinnah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74263,
    "questionText": " On the basis of the process of their formation; which soil is formed differently from the other three?",
    "answerText": " Regur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74264,
    "questionText": " Which book was written by Graham Greene?",
    "answerText": " The Power and Glory"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74265,
    "questionText": " Who introduced the term anticyclone for the first time?",
    "answerText": " F. Galton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74266,
    "questionText": " Which explains that all the galaxies are receding from?",
    "answerText": " Red shift"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74267,
    "questionText": " Summer Solstice in the Southern Hemisphere occurs in which month?",
    "answerText": " 22-Dec-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74268,
    "questionText": " How are the magnetic field lines in the middle of a solenoid?",
    "answerText": " Parallel to the axis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74269,
    "questionText": " The removal of rock; layer by layer due to weathering what is called?",
    "answerText": " Exfoliation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74270,
    "questionText": " Which event was characterised by Montague as ‘Preventive Murder’?",
    "answerText": " Massacre of Jallianwala Bagh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74271,
    "questionText": " Which region does not receives much rainfall in the south-west monsoon season?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu coast"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74272,
    "questionText": " Where is pearl fishing well developed in India?",
    "answerText": " Off the coast at Rameshwaram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74273,
    "questionText": " Which does not have a unit of Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd (HAL)?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74274,
    "questionText": " The first major inscription in classical Sanskrit is that of which king?",
    "answerText": " Rudradaman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74275,
    "questionText": " Which Veda contains an account of magical charms and spells?",
    "answerText": " Atharvaveda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74276,
    "questionText": " Which planet take maximum time for one revolution around the Sun?",
    "answerText": " Jupiter"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74277,
    "questionText": " Which part of the cell is essential for protein synthesis?",
    "answerText": " Ribosomes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74278,
    "questionText": " Which root contain nitroen fixing bacteria?",
    "answerText": " Nodulated root"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74279,
    "questionText": " The basis of European Union began with the signing of which treaty?",
    "answerText": " Maastricht Treaty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74280,
    "questionText": " Which city is associated with the river Mekong?",
    "answerText": " Phnom-Penh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74281,
    "questionText": " Why does the phenomenon of ‘trade winds’ takes place?",
    "answerText": " Due to convection of heat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74282,
    "questionText": " Where are the oceanic current named as ‘Kuroshio; Kurile and Alaskan’ located?",
    "answerText": " North Pacific Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74283,
    "questionText": " Which country has won women’s World Cup Kabaddi?",
    "answerText": " India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74284,
    "questionText": " By which bill does the government make arrangement for the collection of revenues for a year?",
    "answerText": " Finance Bill"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74285,
    "questionText": " Indian President and Prime Minister are a replica of the heads of the State of which country?",
    "answerText": " Britain"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74286,
    "questionText": " What the wind is deflected due of the rotation of the earth?",
    "answerText": " Geostropic wind"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74287,
    "questionText": " Where did Shahjahan build the Moti Masjid?",
    "answerText": " Agra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74288,
    "questionText": " What is the name of the group of languages spoken by the largest number of people in India?",
    "answerText": " Indo-Aryan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74289,
    "questionText": " What interested a nomologist?",
    "answerText": " Scientific Laws"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74290,
    "questionText": " Who was the first person to cross the Alps with army?",
    "answerText": " Hannibal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74291,
    "questionText": " Why is genetic diversity in agricultural crops threatened?",
    "answerText": " Extensive intercropping"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74292,
    "questionText": " Amir Khusarau; the ‘Parrot of India’; was born at which place?",
    "answerText": " Patiali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74293,
    "questionText": " Which effect shows particle nature of height?",
    "answerText": " Photoelectric effect"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74294,
    "questionText": " Who among the following has issued the coin rupee for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Shershah Suri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74295,
    "questionText": " Mac Mohan Line demarcates the boundary between which countries?",
    "answerText": " India and China"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74296,
    "questionText": " Which is most prone to earthquakes?",
    "answerText": " Young folded mountains"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74297,
    "questionText": " First Telephone exchange was opened at Kolkata with 50 lines in?",
    "answerText": 1881
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74298,
    "questionText": " By which force can fat be separated from milk in a cream separator?",
    "answerText": " Centrifugal force"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74299,
    "questionText": " ‘Kandla’ situated on the Gulf of Kachchh is well known for which purpose?",
    "answerText": " Export processing zone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74300,
    "questionText": " Which place has no Ashokan edicts?",
    "answerText": " Pataliputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74301,
    "questionText": " When the Vice-President officiates as President; whose salary does he draw?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74302,
    "questionText": " Which lake in India has the highest water salinity?",
    "answerText": " Sambhar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74303,
    "questionText": " Which atmospheric layer that reflects radio waves is called?",
    "answerText": " Ionosphere"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74304,
    "questionText": " Which region of northern India was not included in the empire of Ala-ud-din Khalji?",
    "answerText": " Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74305,
    "questionText": " Which would be the shortest route from San Francisco to Vladivostok?",
    "answerText": " Flying over the Pacific Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74306,
    "questionText": " What is the total number of High Courts in India at present?",
    "answerText": 24
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74307,
    "questionText": " Which Sultan built the fifth storeys of Qutub Minar?",
    "answerText": " Firoz Shah Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74308,
    "questionText": " Who laid the foundations of Portuguese power in India?",
    "answerText": " Alfonso de Albuquerque"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74309,
    "questionText": " How can the quantity of water vapour the atmosphere hold increases?",
    "answerText": " With increase of temperature"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74310,
    "questionText": " Who among the following was an eminent Painter?",
    "answerText": " Sarada Ukil"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74311,
    "questionText": " From where can renewable energy be obtained?",
    "answerText": " Biomass"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74312,
    "questionText": " Which is a strong smelling agent added to LPG cylinder to help in the detection of gas leakage?",
    "answerText": " Thioethanol"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74313,
    "questionText": " Which river flows through Maharashtra and Gujarat?",
    "answerText": " Tapti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74314,
    "questionText": " Who owned a sword called Crocea mors or yellow death?",
    "answerText": " Julius Caesar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74315,
    "questionText": " Which component of plants receives stimulus for flowering?",
    "answerText": " Leaves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74316,
    "questionText": " Who was instrumental in bringing the Extremists and the Moderates together at Lucknow?",
    "answerText": " Annie Besant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74317,
    "questionText": " How many times has National Emergency been declared?",
    "answerText": " Three times"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74318,
    "questionText": " Niagara Falls is located between which pair of lakes?",
    "answerText": " Lake Erie and Lake Ontario"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74319,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the famous novel ‘Gone with the Wind’?",
    "answerText": " Charles Dickens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74320,
    "questionText": " Which group have quantities that do not have the same dimension?",
    "answerText": " Force; Impulse"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74321,
    "questionText": " Which Indian ruler established embassies in foreign countries. on modern lines?",
    "answerText": " Tipu Sultan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74322,
    "questionText": " Who discovered the laws of planetary orbits?",
    "answerText": " Johannes Kepler"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74323,
    "questionText": " Which was the first fort constructed by the British in India?",
    "answerText": " Fort St. George"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74324,
    "questionText": " Which nitrogen fixing bacteria is found in leguminuous plant?",
    "answerText": " Rizobium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74325,
    "questionText": " Which UN agency has its headquarters at Paris?",
    "answerText": " UNESCO"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74326,
    "questionText": " In the context of the reign of Guptas and their successors; what is Vishti'?",
    "answerText": " Forced labour"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74327,
    "questionText": " What is the word used to describe the shape of earth?",
    "answerText": " Oblate spheroid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74328,
    "questionText": " Which cell organelle is responsible for cellular respiration?",
    "answerText": " Mitochondrium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74329,
    "questionText": " Acetylene is used as an anaesthetic under which name?",
    "answerText": " Narcylene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74330,
    "questionText": " Which is the most important divinity of Rigveda?",
    "answerText": " Varuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74331,
    "questionText": " In which country; has maximum damage to the forest been caused by acid rain?",
    "answerText": " Poland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74332,
    "questionText": " Indian sovereignity in sea extends upto how many nautical miles?",
    "answerText": 12
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74333,
    "questionText": " What is the source of immediate energy for cellular activity?",
    "answerText": " ATP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74334,
    "questionText": " Which is responsible for converting milk into curd?",
    "answerText": " Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74335,
    "questionText": " The number of wives of which Mughal ruler ‘fell short even of the Quranic allowance of four’?",
    "answerText": " Aurangzeb"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74336,
    "questionText": " Near the banks of which river excavations have brought to light that Indus Valley Civilization percolated to far south?",
    "answerText": " Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74337,
    "questionText": " The book ‘Around the World in Eighty Days’ was written by which person?",
    "answerText": " Jules Verne"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74338,
    "questionText": " Where will be the Time period in a vibration magnetometer infinite?",
    "answerText": " At magnetic pole"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74339,
    "questionText": " The inspiration of ‘Liberty; Equality and Fraternity’ was derived from which revolution?",
    "answerText": " French revolution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74340,
    "questionText": " With which the executive power relating to concurrent subjects remain?",
    "answerText": " The Centre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74341,
    "questionText": " Which year is celebrated as International Year of Forests?",
    "answerText": " 2001-2010"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74342,
    "questionText": " What does a permanent magnet repel?",
    "answerText": " Diamagnetic substances only"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74343,
    "questionText": " Moho discontinuity lies at the depth of approximately how many kilometers?",
    "answerText": " 400 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74344,
    "questionText": " Who is associated with the Local Self- Government Act?",
    "answerText": " Ripon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74345,
    "questionText": " Purification of petroleum is carried out by which method?",
    "answerText": " Fractional distillation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74346,
    "questionText": " Which plant yeilds biodiesel or biofuel?",
    "answerText": " Jatropha curcas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74347,
    "questionText": " In the realm of coal production in the world; what is the rank of India?",
    "answerText": " Fourth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74348,
    "questionText": " In which year did Mahatma Gandhi enter into freedom struggle in India?",
    "answerText": 1917
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74349,
    "questionText": " Which upheaval took place in Bengal immediately after the Revolt of 1857?",
    "answerText": " Indigo Disturbances"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74350,
    "questionText": " Who broke Pete Sampras’s record of maximum Grand Slams in tennis?",
    "answerText": " Roger Federer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74351,
    "questionText": " Which is the State having the largest population of scheduled castes?",
    "answerText": " Utter Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74352,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Defence Minister of India?",
    "answerText": " N. Gopalaswami Ayyangar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74353,
    "questionText": " What is the frequency of a wave whose time-period is 05 second?",
    "answerText": " 20 Hz"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74354,
    "questionText": " Who was impeached in England for his actions in India?",
    "answerText": " Warren Hastings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74355,
    "questionText": " In which type of coal percentage of carbon is the highest?",
    "answerText": " Anthracite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74356,
    "questionText": " If a U-238 nucleus splits into two identical parts; how will the two nuclei be so produced?",
    "answerText": " Stable"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74357,
    "questionText": " What is the main objective of Antyodaya programme?",
    "answerText": " Uplift the poor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74358,
    "questionText": " When was the Constituent Assembly for undivided India first met?",
    "answerText": " 9th December; 1946"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74359,
    "questionText": " With whom was the last opportunity to avoid the partition of India lost?",
    "answerText": " Cabinet Mission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74360,
    "questionText": " Long treeless grassy palms are characteristics of which grass?",
    "answerText": " Pampas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74361,
    "questionText": " The Pacific Islands from New Guinea south east-wards to the Fiji Islands’ what is this group called?",
    "answerText": " The Mellanesia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74362,
    "questionText": " The famous sportsman Michael Jordan is associated with which game?",
    "answerText": " Basket ball"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74363,
    "questionText": " The latitude of a place expresses its angular position relative to the place of which point?",
    "answerText": " Equator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74364,
    "questionText": " In absence of ribosome in cell which function does not takes place?",
    "answerText": " Protein synthesis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74365,
    "questionText": " A Money Bill passed by the Lok Sabha has to be passed/returned by Rajya Sabha within how many days?",
    "answerText": " 14 days"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74366,
    "questionText": " In which city is the Global Automotive Research Centre being set up?",
    "answerText": " Chennai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74367,
    "questionText": " By whom wasIsland of Bombay was given to the English Prince Charles II as dowry?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74368,
    "questionText": " Fado is a musical style popular in which country?",
    "answerText": " Portugal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74369,
    "questionText": " After how many years is Election of Rajya Sabha held?",
    "answerText": " 2years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74370,
    "questionText": " What is the normal temperature of the human body?",
    "answerText": " 98.4°F"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74371,
    "questionText": " In India; which type of forest occupy the largest area?",
    "answerText": " Tropical Moist Deciduous Forest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74372,
    "questionText": " In which activity percentage share of cooperative sector is the highest?",
    "answerText": " Sugar production"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74373,
    "questionText": " What does a hygrometer measure?",
    "answerText": " Humidity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74374,
    "questionText": " How many languages are used on a ten rupee note?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74375,
    "questionText": " What is the sacred animal of Thailand?",
    "answerText": " The white elephant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74376,
    "questionText": " Insectivorous plant generally grow in soil which is deficient in which gas?",
    "answerText": " Nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74377,
    "questionText": " Which distinguishes the Harappan from other contemporary civilizations of the world?",
    "answerText": " Town planning and drainage"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74378,
    "questionText": " Who were the two great Mughal rulers who wrote their own memoirs?",
    "answerText": " Babar and Jahangir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74379,
    "questionText": " Which country was readmitted to the Olympics after her 21 year suspension?",
    "answerText": " South Africa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74380,
    "questionText": " How is Missile ‘Astra’?",
    "answerText": " A air to air missile"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74381,
    "questionText": " Ben Johnson (Canadian) was disqualified in the 1998 Seoul Olympic in the Athletics?",
    "answerText": " 100 m"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74382,
    "questionText": " Who discovered Anopheles mosquito transmit malaria?",
    "answerText": " Ronal ross"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74383,
    "questionText": " Why is Poverty in less developed countries largely?",
    "answerText": " Due to income inequality"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74384,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest tribal community in India?",
    "answerText": " Gonds"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74385,
    "questionText": " By whom was the largest grant of villages to temples and brahmanas given?",
    "answerText": " The Guptas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74386,
    "questionText": " Which country makes maximum use of the geothermal energy?",
    "answerText": " Iceland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74387,
    "questionText": " In which years did the Right to Information Act come into force?",
    "answerText": 2005
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74388,
    "questionText": " Which layer of the earth is believed to have the heaviest mineral materials of highest density?",
    "answerText": " Central core"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74389,
    "questionText": " Which writ is issued by the court in’ case of illegal detention of a person?",
    "answerText": " Habeas Corpus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74390,
    "questionText": " By whom was the 'Shahnama' written?",
    "answerText": " Firdausi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74391,
    "questionText": " Who is the chairman of 13th Finance Commission?",
    "answerText": " Vijay Kelkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74392,
    "questionText": " Between which set of blood groups; is the blood transfusion possible?",
    "answerText": " A and AB (A donor)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74393,
    "questionText": " Which Bacteria is found in the intestine of human?",
    "answerText": " Escherichia coli"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74394,
    "questionText": " The Govt. of India does not provide any direct financial assistance to which scheme?",
    "answerText": " Jeevan Sathi Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74395,
    "questionText": " Which animal breathes through the skin?",
    "answerText": " Frog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74396,
    "questionText": " To whom is the Chief Minister of a State responsible?",
    "answerText": " Governor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74397,
    "questionText": " When can the salaries of High Court judges be reduced?",
    "answerText": " During a Financial Emergency"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74398,
    "questionText": " A hydrogen atom is paramagnetic. What is a hydrogen molecule?",
    "answerText": " Diamagnetic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74399,
    "questionText": " Which country produced 127 lakh metric tones fish in 2010?",
    "answerText": " Japan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74400,
    "questionText": " If a proton of mass m is moving with velocity of light; how will its mass?",
    "answerText": " Unchanged"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74401,
    "questionText": " Where did Moplah rebellion of 1921 take place?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74402,
    "questionText": " Ankaleshwar in India is known for the production of which state?",
    "answerText": " Assam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74403,
    "questionText": " Which country in Africa has luxurious tropical rain forests?",
    "answerText": " Ivory coast"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74404,
    "questionText": " Who was associated with Kakori Conspiracy case?",
    "answerText": " Ashfaqulla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74405,
    "questionText": " What is laughing gas?",
    "answerText": " Nitrous oxide"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74406,
    "questionText": " What is the approximate equatorial circumference of the earth?",
    "answerText": " 40;000 Km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74407,
    "questionText": " How many number of atomic power plants existing in India today?",
    "answerText": 9
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74408,
    "questionText": " By whom was the most important theory of general biology proposed?",
    "answerText": " Darwin and Wallace"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74409,
    "questionText": " Which is the oldest Development Financial Institution of India?",
    "answerText": " IFCI"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74410,
    "questionText": " The concept of carbon credit originated from which protocal?",
    "answerText": " Kyoto Protocol"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74411,
    "questionText": " Which disease is characterised by inflammation of the membranes covering the brain and spinal cord?",
    "answerText": " Meningitis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74412,
    "questionText": " Which is the headquarters of World Trade Organisation (WTO)?",
    "answerText": " Geneva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74413,
    "questionText": " Kourou city is well-known for which purpose?",
    "answerText": " Satellite launching"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74414,
    "questionText": " National Agricultural Cooperative Marketing Federation is known what?",
    "answerText": " NACMF"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74415,
    "questionText": " Why did Mahmud of Ghazni attack India?",
    "answerText": " To establish his empire in India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74416,
    "questionText": " Which field is used to produce deflection in a television picture tube?",
    "answerText": " A magnetic fields"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74417,
    "questionText": " Of which dynasty does Vishnu Purana give an account?",
    "answerText": " Mauryan dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74418,
    "questionText": " How does the earth rotate around its axis?",
    "answerText": " From west to east"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74419,
    "questionText": " What is the name for the number 1 followed by 100 zeros?",
    "answerText": " Google"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74420,
    "questionText": " The name Kunjarani Devi is associated with which game?",
    "answerText": " Weight lifting"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74421,
    "questionText": " Which soil is best suited for cotton?",
    "answerText": " Regur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74422,
    "questionText": " 38 N and 12 E are the respective latitude and longitude of which places?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74423,
    "questionText": " Which substance is used as antiknock compound?",
    "answerText": " TEL"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74424,
    "questionText": " What was the most profound influence on the drafting of the Indian Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Government of India Act; 1935"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74425,
    "questionText": " Which is the greatest known ocean depth (which lies in the Pacific Ocean)?",
    "answerText": " 11;033 m"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74426,
    "questionText": " Which is the longest railway platform?",
    "answerText": " Kharagpur (India)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74427,
    "questionText": " Which was the first woman to climb Mount Everest?",
    "answerText": " Junko Tabei"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74428,
    "questionText": " What is the Study of pulse and arterial blood pressure called?",
    "answerText": " Sphygmology"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74429,
    "questionText": " Litmus paper used in laboratary from which obtained?",
    "answerText": " Lichen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74430,
    "questionText": " India reached the final of the Davis Cup for the first time in which year?",
    "answerText": 1966
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74431,
    "questionText": " Which part of the pitcher plant becomes modified into a pitcher?",
    "answerText": " Leaf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74432,
    "questionText": " Which ruler of Vijayanagar had sent his embassy to the emperor of China?",
    "answerText": " Bukka I"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74433,
    "questionText": " Total internal reflection can take place when light travels from which thing?",
    "answerText": " Diamond to glass"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74434,
    "questionText": " Which; ancient' Indian King claimed ekarat (the sole sovereign) or the first Imperial ruler of India?",
    "answerText": " Udayin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74435,
    "questionText": " Which contain high content of lead?",
    "answerText": " High octane fuel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74436,
    "questionText": " What type of Party system has been evolved in India?",
    "answerText": " Multi-Party"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74437,
    "questionText": " The Vindhyas belong to which class of mountains?",
    "answerText": " Block mountains"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74438,
    "questionText": " Where is the mausoleum of Sher Shah?",
    "answerText": " Sasaram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74439,
    "questionText": " What is ikebana?",
    "answerText": " Flower arranging"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74440,
    "questionText": " What was the greatest invention of man in Palaeolithic Age?",
    "answerText": " Fire"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74441,
    "questionText": " In which battle Porus was defeated by Alexander?",
    "answerText": " Hydaspes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74442,
    "questionText": " Regional Rural Banks are designed to work in which ideal?",
    "answerText": " Help the targetted groups"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74443,
    "questionText": " Where does the cold Labrador current bring nine months winter?",
    "answerText": " Eastern Newfoundland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74444,
    "questionText": " Who started the Public Works Department in India in 1848?",
    "answerText": " Lord Dalhousie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74445,
    "questionText": " By whom was the clarion call ‘Dilli Chalo’ was given?",
    "answerText": " Subhash Chandra Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74446,
    "questionText": " Which biomass has the highest species diversity?",
    "answerText": " Tropical rainforests"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74447,
    "questionText": " Who was the 1st President of BCCI (Board of Control for Cricket in India)?",
    "answerText": " R.E. Grant Govan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74448,
    "questionText": " Which feature is the product of vulcanicity?",
    "answerText": " Caldera"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74449,
    "questionText": " Which types of light are strongly absorbed by plants?",
    "answerText": " Blue and red"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74450,
    "questionText": " BMD testing is done to diagnose which disease?",
    "answerText": " Osteoporosis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74451,
    "questionText": " In which terms is the Rate of growth of an economy measured?",
    "answerText": " National income"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74452,
    "questionText": " The Kingdom of Vijayanagar came into existence during which reign?",
    "answerText": " Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74453,
    "questionText": " What type of farming is practised in the densely populated regions of the world?",
    "answerText": " Intensive farming"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74454,
    "questionText": " Who was elected as the President of All-India Khilafat Conference when it met at Delhi in 1919?",
    "answerText": " Mahatma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74455,
    "questionText": " Which is most efficient engine?",
    "answerText": " Electric"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74456,
    "questionText": " Which is the hottest planet?",
    "answerText": " Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74457,
    "questionText": " What does the special status of Jammu and Kashmir imply?",
    "answerText": " A separate Constitution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74458,
    "questionText": " By whom was the Constitution of India adopted?",
    "answerText": " Constituent Assembly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74459,
    "questionText": " When is International Talk like a Pirate Day is observed?",
    "answerText": " 19-Sep-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74460,
    "questionText": " With the rise of temperature; what will be the surface tension of a liquid?",
    "answerText": " Decreases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74461,
    "questionText": " What is an organisation’s introductory web page?",
    "answerText": " Vortal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74462,
    "questionText": " Which is printed on a commonly used fluorescent tube light?",
    "answerText": " 6500 k"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74463,
    "questionText": " If the cash-reserve ratio is lowered by the Central bank; what will be its effect on credit creation?",
    "answerText": " Increase"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74464,
    "questionText": " What is in a healthy person rate of heart beat on one minute?",
    "answerText": " 72 times"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74465,
    "questionText": " What is the most important requirement for the people of a flood hit area?",
    "answerText": " Inoculation against cholera"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74466,
    "questionText": " Prithviraj Chauhan belonged to which Rajput dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Gahadavalas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74467,
    "questionText": " Who was the first speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Malgaonkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74468,
    "questionText": " What was the first venture of Gandhiji in all-India politics?",
    "answerText": " Rowlatt Satyagraha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74469,
    "questionText": " Vascular cambium and corck cambium is the example of which thing?",
    "answerText": " Lateral meristem"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74470,
    "questionText": " In which latitudes are the seasonal contrasts maximum?",
    "answerText": " Mid latitudes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74471,
    "questionText": " Where is the Shrine of Hazarat Nizamuddin Auliya is situated?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74472,
    "questionText": " The Ilbert Bill agitation led to ‘the foundation of which conference?",
    "answerText": " All India National Conference"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74473,
    "questionText": " Which vitamin is synthesised in the body by intestinal bacteria?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin K"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74474,
    "questionText": " Which is the official language of Bank of Central African States?",
    "answerText": " French"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74475,
    "questionText": " What is an example of emulsion?",
    "answerText": " Milk"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74476,
    "questionText": " In India; how many States share the coastline?",
    "answerText": 9
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74477,
    "questionText": " Nanda Devi peak forms a part of which range?",
    "answerText": " Kumaon Himalayas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74478,
    "questionText": " Who was THE woman to Sherlock Holmes?",
    "answerText": " Irene Adler"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74479,
    "questionText": " The Hindustan steel Ltd. Durgapur has been set up with the help of which country?",
    "answerText": " United kingdom"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74480,
    "questionText": " Which compound does not contains an OH group?",
    "answerText": " Aldehyde"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74481,
    "questionText": " Who was assigned the first Iqta in India by Mohammad Ghori?",
    "answerText": " Qutbuddin Aibak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74482,
    "questionText": " Which state of India is the largest producer of lignite coal?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74483,
    "questionText": " The National Housing Bank was set up in India as a wholly-owned subsidiary of which bank?",
    "answerText": " Reserve Bank of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74484,
    "questionText": " Which is not an award given on the National Awards Day?",
    "answerText": " Vishwamitra Award"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74485,
    "questionText": " Which is at the apex of Industrial Finance in India?",
    "answerText": " Industrial Development Bank of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74486,
    "questionText": " Which current is produced by upwelling of cold water?",
    "answerText": " Benzuela current"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74487,
    "questionText": " Which is the longest bone in the human body?",
    "answerText": " Thigh bone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74488,
    "questionText": " AT which °C water has maximum density?",
    "answerText": " 4°C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74489,
    "questionText": " The nitrogen percentage is the highest in which fertilizer?",
    "answerText": " Urea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74490,
    "questionText": " In human body; which hormone regulates blood calcium and phosphate?",
    "answerText": " Parathyroid hormone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74491,
    "questionText": " For a body moving with constant speed in a horizontal circle; what remains constant?",
    "answerText": " KE"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74492,
    "questionText": " Which is not essentially a species of the Himalayan vegetation?",
    "answerText": " Mahogany"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74493,
    "questionText": " The Battle of Khanwa in 1527 was fought between which rulers?",
    "answerText": " Babur and Rana Sanga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74494,
    "questionText": " Sunda Trench lies in which ocean?",
    "answerText": " Indian Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74495,
    "questionText": " To which process is the term CMYK related?",
    "answerText": " Offset printing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74496,
    "questionText": " By whom was collective responsibility of the Cabinet introduced in India?",
    "answerText": " Constitution of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74497,
    "questionText": " ‘Man-The Maker of His Own Destiny’ book was written by which person?",
    "answerText": " Swami Vivekananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74498,
    "questionText": " Which is used in beauty parlours for’ hair setting?",
    "answerText": " Sulphur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74499,
    "questionText": " What is the range of Prithvi III; the naval version of Prithvi?",
    "answerText": " 250 km-300 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74500,
    "questionText": " What is the highest denomination of currency notes in circulation as legal tender in India at present?",
    "answerText": " Rs.1000"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74501,
    "questionText": " Who invented the television?",
    "answerText": " John Logie Baird"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74502,
    "questionText": " Which country ranks top in the mining of gold?",
    "answerText": " South Africa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74503,
    "questionText": " Which is the official language of West African Development Bank?",
    "answerText": " French"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74504,
    "questionText": " Which Committee was formed to suggest means for eradicating black money?",
    "answerText": " Cheiliah Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74505,
    "questionText": " Which term for natural vegetation is associated with Siberia?",
    "answerText": " Taiga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74506,
    "questionText": " Which Governor of Bengal committed suicide in 1774?",
    "answerText": " Robert Clive"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74507,
    "questionText": " By which ministry is Economic survey published?",
    "answerText": " Ministry of Finance"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74508,
    "questionText": " Which Gupta ruler had led a campaign to the south and was an expert 'Veena' player?",
    "answerText": " Samudragupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74509,
    "questionText": " What is the largest ecosystem of the Earth?",
    "answerText": " Hydrosphere"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74510,
    "questionText": " When the wind is deflected due to the rotation of the Earth; what is it called?",
    "answerText": " Geostropic wind"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74511,
    "questionText": " Who contributed the Chalukya in Western India?",
    "answerText": " Guptas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74512,
    "questionText": " During whose reign did the Mongols first invade India?",
    "answerText": " Iltutmish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74513,
    "questionText": " Which city was superman born in?",
    "answerText": " Kryptonopolis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74514,
    "questionText": " What is the capitol of the United Arab Emirates?",
    "answerText": " Abu Dhabi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74515,
    "questionText": " The Laxman Era was started (in 1119 AD) by which dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Sens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74516,
    "questionText": " Parthenocarpy fruit is obtained by which sprying phytohormone?",
    "answerText": " Auxins"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74517,
    "questionText": " Azola anabana is used as fertilizer in growing which crop?",
    "answerText": " Rice"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74518,
    "questionText": " Between which was the battle of Dharmat fought?",
    "answerText": " Aurangzeb and Dara Shikoh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74519,
    "questionText": " Which Mughals is regarded more as an adventurer than a ruler?",
    "answerText": " Babar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74520,
    "questionText": " Which is the most important item of non-plan expenditure?",
    "answerText": " Interest payment"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74521,
    "questionText": " What is Snow line?",
    "answerText": " The altitude above which snow never melts"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74522,
    "questionText": " In which State are Namchik-Namphuk Coalfields located?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74523,
    "questionText": " India is the world’s largest producer as well as the consumer of which crops?",
    "answerText": " Pules"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74524,
    "questionText": " During the time of Harshavardhana; where was a great Buddhist assembly held?",
    "answerText": " Prayag"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74525,
    "questionText": " What was the rate of land revenue as 'given in the dharma shastras?",
    "answerText": " 6-Jan-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74526,
    "questionText": " Which organisation prepares topographical maps of India?",
    "answerText": " Geographical Survey of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74527,
    "questionText": " Who wrote the book ‘Planned Economy for India’?",
    "answerText": " M. Visvesvaraya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74528,
    "questionText": " If you want to visit sambhar lake; to which state you will go?",
    "answerText": " Rajasthan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74529,
    "questionText": " Which river demarcate the partial boundary between South Africa and Botswana?",
    "answerText": " Limpopo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74530,
    "questionText": " What is the ultimate cause of water movement in a plant stem against gravity?",
    "answerText": " Osmosis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74531,
    "questionText": " With which field is Begum Akhtar associated?",
    "answerText": " Vocal Music"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74532,
    "questionText": " The first Governor-General of India was appointed under the provisions of which act?",
    "answerText": " Act of 1833"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74533,
    "questionText": " Which first Europeans came to India?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74534,
    "questionText": " Who said ‘At the stroke of midnight; when the world sleeps; India will awake to life and freedom’?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74535,
    "questionText": " Which can be abolished but not dissolved?",
    "answerText": " State Legislative Council"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74536,
    "questionText": " Which state is the largest producer of black pepper in India?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74537,
    "questionText": " When did Mr. Attlee; Prime Minister of England; announce tile transfer of power to the Indians?",
    "answerText": " June; 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74538,
    "questionText": " Which is not a direct tax?",
    "answerText": " Tax on entertainment"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74539,
    "questionText": " Which is not the part of North Atlantic ocean current system?",
    "answerText": " Brazilian current"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74540,
    "questionText": " How is angular speed of a whirlwind in a tornado towards the centre?",
    "answerText": " Decreases rapidly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74541,
    "questionText": " By which is in practice the policy of the Government shaped?",
    "answerText": " The Cabinet"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74542,
    "questionText": " The electron emitted in beta radiation originates from where?",
    "answerText": " Inner orbits of atoms"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74543,
    "questionText": " When was Inter-Governmental Authori on Development come into existence?",
    "answerText": " 21st March; 1996"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74544,
    "questionText": " During which ruler did Bernier visit India?",
    "answerText": " Shahjahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74545,
    "questionText": " For which period does Mayor of a Municipal Corporation hold the office?",
    "answerText": " 1 year"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74546,
    "questionText": " Which element is depleted most from the soil after a crop is harvested?",
    "answerText": " Potassium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74547,
    "questionText": " Which is a round worm that enters man’s body through the soles of the feet?",
    "answerText": " Hookworm"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74548,
    "questionText": " Which country is situated geographically in America but politically a part of Europe?",
    "answerText": " Green Land"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74549,
    "questionText": " At which city is Largest mint in India located?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74550,
    "questionText": " For the measurement of temperature of the order of 400°C; what will we prefer?",
    "answerText": " Thermocouple"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74551,
    "questionText": " Why was Mashelkar Committee constituted?",
    "answerText": " Auto fuel policy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74552,
    "questionText": " Which ilement is in the highest amount in the composition of basalt rock?",
    "answerText": " Silicon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74553,
    "questionText": " What can be the maximum duration of totality for a solar eclipse?",
    "answerText": " 7 minutes 40 seconds"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74554,
    "questionText": " Which are the oldest mountains in India according to geographical history?",
    "answerText": " Aravallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74555,
    "questionText": " Who Chola king fought against the Shailendia king of Shri Vijaya and defeated him?",
    "answerText": " Rajendra Chola I"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74556,
    "questionText": " In the Delhi Sultanate; which administrative unit called Paragana was headed by an official?",
    "answerText": " Amil"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74557,
    "questionText": " Who was the Greek ambassador in the' court of Chandragupta Maurya?",
    "answerText": " Megasthenese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74558,
    "questionText": " By whom were Species Plantarum and Systema Natural written?",
    "answerText": " Linneus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74559,
    "questionText": " The Portuguese traveller; Nuniz visited Vijayanagar during the reign of which ruler?",
    "answerText": " Achyuta Raya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74560,
    "questionText": " The Imperial Bank of India; after nationalisation was given the name of which bank?",
    "answerText": " State Bank of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74561,
    "questionText": " In 1901 which brand of car was seen for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Mercedes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74562,
    "questionText": " In which country are the broken hill famous for zinc and lead?",
    "answerText": " Australia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74563,
    "questionText": " Under the Constitution; the residuary powers vest with which government?",
    "answerText": " Union Government"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74564,
    "questionText": " Asia has large areas of inland drainage. Why is it so?",
    "answerText": " Rainfall is seasonal and scanty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74565,
    "questionText": " In storms; the roofs of some houses are carried away. According whom is this?",
    "answerText": " Bernoulli’s principle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74566,
    "questionText": " Which Sikh Guru who was killed by the orders of Aurangzeb?",
    "answerText": " Guru Teg Bahadur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74567,
    "questionText": " Which shipyard is known for the manufacture of bargets; coasters and dredgers?",
    "answerText": " Garden Reach Shipyard"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74568,
    "questionText": " In which direction of flow of stream is controlled by rock structure?",
    "answerText": " Consequent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74569,
    "questionText": " By whom are the Chief Justice and other Judges of the High Court are appointed?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74570,
    "questionText": " To which age the Indus Valley Civilization belongs?",
    "answerText": " Neolithic age"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74571,
    "questionText": " Which region of India was ruled by Sultan Zainul Abidin?",
    "answerText": " Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74572,
    "questionText": " Where was the resolution to start the Quit India Movement adopted by INC at its session?",
    "answerText": " Bombay"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74573,
    "questionText": " By which bank are the central banking functions in India performed?",
    "answerText": " Reserve Bank of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74574,
    "questionText": " The performance of which industry is considered performance of the core industry?",
    "answerText": " Oil and Petroleum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74575,
    "questionText": " When was the decimal system of currency introduced in India?",
    "answerText": 1957
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74576,
    "questionText": " Which industry does not earn foreign exchange for India?",
    "answerText": " Fertilizers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74577,
    "questionText": " Who has the power to form a new State within the Union of India?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74578,
    "questionText": " Which continent has the highest density of population?",
    "answerText": " Europe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74579,
    "questionText": " Phosgene is obtained by the reaction of carbon monoxide and which gas?",
    "answerText": " Chlorine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74580,
    "questionText": " What digit does not exist in Roman Numerals?",
    "answerText": " Zero"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74581,
    "questionText": " Heat given to an ideal gas under isothermal conditions is used in which work?",
    "answerText": " In doing external work"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74582,
    "questionText": " Who is called the Father of English Poetry?",
    "answerText": " Chaucer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74583,
    "questionText": " Which is the gas usually filled in the electric bulb?",
    "answerText": " Nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74584,
    "questionText": " Which temple got the name of Black Pagoda?",
    "answerText": " Sun Temple"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74585,
    "questionText": " Where is Dead sea situated?",
    "answerText": " A Rift Valley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74586,
    "questionText": " What is a graph is plotted taking °C along the Y-axis and of K along the X-axis?",
    "answerText": " Straight line"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74587,
    "questionText": " What did the name ‘Ratnakara’ denoted In ancient Indian historical geography?",
    "answerText": " The Indian Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74588,
    "questionText": " Who was the first leader of the Opposition in the Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Kamlapati Tripathi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74589,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Indian to win an individual medal in Olympics?",
    "answerText": " K.D. Yadav"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74590,
    "questionText": " Which is not helpful for delta formation?",
    "answerText": " Tidal nature of waves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74591,
    "questionText": " In which animal is respiration done by skin?",
    "answerText": " Frog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74592,
    "questionText": " Which is the element common to all acids?",
    "answerText": " Hydrogen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74593,
    "questionText": " On whom was the title ‘Punjab Kesari’ was conferred?",
    "answerText": " Lala Lajpat Rai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74594,
    "questionText": " With which India’s progress has been reasonably satisfactory in connection?",
    "answerText": " Growth of GNP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74595,
    "questionText": " Which pairs of rays is electromagnetic in nature?",
    "answerText": " x-rays and gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74596,
    "questionText": " During the freedom struggle; who established ‘The Deccan Educational Society’?",
    "answerText": " M. G. Ranade"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74597,
    "questionText": " In the history of the freedom movement of India; the year 1930 is associated with which event?",
    "answerText": " Dandi March"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74598,
    "questionText": " Which was the first Indian woman to scale Mount Everest?",
    "answerText": " Bachendri Pal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74599,
    "questionText": " Of which Religion-wise the sculpture were found at Kankali tila in Mathura?",
    "answerText": " Jaina"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74600,
    "questionText": " Which has geographical position of degree latitude and degree longitude?",
    "answerText": " In the South Atlantic Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74601,
    "questionText": " The extent of the Delhi Sultanate empire was the greatest during which reign?",
    "answerText": " Alauddin Khilji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74602,
    "questionText": " White lung disease is prevalent among the worker of which industry?",
    "answerText": " Cotton Industry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74603,
    "questionText": " Which nontoxic gas helps in formation of enzymes which ripen fruit?",
    "answerText": " Acetylene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74604,
    "questionText": " Which vegetation is called natural cattle country?",
    "answerText": " Downs"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74605,
    "questionText": " In the human body which sturcture is the appendix attached to?",
    "answerText": " Large intestine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74606,
    "questionText": " Which ecosystem covers the largest area of the earth’s surface?",
    "answerText": " Marine Ecosystem"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74607,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of the UN Industrial Development Organization?",
    "answerText": " Vienna; Austria"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74608,
    "questionText": " What is the period of revolution of a geostationary satellite?",
    "answerText": " 24 hours"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74609,
    "questionText": " Which thing acts as an antidote to HgCl2 poisoning?",
    "answerText": " White of egg"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74610,
    "questionText": " One calorie is the heat required to raise the temperature of 1g of water by how many degrees?",
    "answerText": " 1 °C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74611,
    "questionText": " Which state has smallest land area?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74612,
    "questionText": " Which relates to the formation of the Himalayas?",
    "answerText": " Folding of the geosyncline"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74613,
    "questionText": " Which colloidal solution is used in photography?",
    "answerText": " Colloidal silver bromite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74614,
    "questionText": " വീഞ്ഞിൽ അടങ്ങിയിരിക്കുന്ന ആസിഡ്? ",
    "answerText": " ടാർടാറിക് ആസിഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74615,
    "questionText": " Which state is the percentage of forest area to total geographical area the highest?",
    "answerText": " Arunachal Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74616,
    "questionText": " On which conservation law; does a rocker work?",
    "answerText": " Angular momentum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74617,
    "questionText": " Who wrote the line: ‘A thing of beauty is a joy for ever’?",
    "answerText": " John Keats"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74618,
    "questionText": " Sound travels faster in which thing?",
    "answerText": " Iron than in air"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74619,
    "questionText": " In which city was Alexander Graham Bell born in 1847?",
    "answerText": " Edinburgh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74620,
    "questionText": " Who was the last ruler of Sunga dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Devabhuti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74621,
    "questionText": " Which hormone contains iodine?",
    "answerText": " Thyroxine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74622,
    "questionText": " A temperature difference of 25°C is equivalent to a temperature difference of how many F?",
    "answerText": " 45° F"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74623,
    "questionText": " What does the Preamble of our Constitution contin?",
    "answerText": " The spirit of the Constitution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74624,
    "questionText": " Who is the executive head of a Municipal Corporation?",
    "answerText": " Commissioner"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74625,
    "questionText": " What is produced during the formation of photochemical smog?",
    "answerText": " Nitrogen oxide"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74626,
    "questionText": " Which country leads in fish catches?",
    "answerText": " Japan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74627,
    "questionText": " If temperature rises; what will be the coefficient of viscosity of liquid?",
    "answerText": " Decreases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74628,
    "questionText": " With reference to Delhi Sultanate; who was the founder of Sayyid Dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Khizr Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74629,
    "questionText": " Which factors are most responsible for disease in plant?",
    "answerText": " Fungi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74630,
    "questionText": " In which nomad man started settling?",
    "answerText": " Neolithic Age"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74631,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Chief of the Air staff?",
    "answerText": " Sir Thomas Elmhirst"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74632,
    "questionText": " Who can initiate impeachment proceedings against the President of India?",
    "answerText": " Either House of Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74633,
    "questionText": " Which of a species describes the tropic function it fills in its environment?",
    "answerText": " Niche"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74634,
    "questionText": " The Government of India adopted the State Emblem of India from the Sarnath Lion Capital of Asoka on?",
    "answerText": " 26th January; 1950"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74635,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest producer of fruits in the Anglo-American Region?",
    "answerText": " California"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74636,
    "questionText": " Which leaders took major initiative in the formation of the League of Nations?",
    "answerText": " Franklin Roosevelt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74637,
    "questionText": " The Earth turns through 360° in 24 hours. How much time does Each 15° longitude represent?",
    "answerText": " One hour"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74638,
    "questionText": " Which is obtained; when H2 S is passed through the solution of sodium zincate?",
    "answerText": " ZnS"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74639,
    "questionText": " A floating body always displaces liquid equal to its which thing?",
    "answerText": " Weight"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74640,
    "questionText": " Which chemically inactive gas present in atmosphere?",
    "answerText": " Argon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74641,
    "questionText": " How is the relative permeability of a diamagnetic material?",
    "answerText": " Less than unity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74642,
    "questionText": " How are the orbits of planets around the Sun; or of satellites around the Earth;?",
    "answerText": " Circular and elliptic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74643,
    "questionText": " In which article Right to education is a fundamental right?",
    "answerText": " Personal liberty under Article 21"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74644,
    "questionText": " Which was the most important factor in transforming ancient Indian society into feudal society?",
    "answerText": " Practice of land grants"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74645,
    "questionText": " The Maratha; confederacy was virtually dissolved after which battle?",
    "answerText": " Third Battle of Panipat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74646,
    "questionText": " By which plants is the maximum fixation of solar energy done?",
    "answerText": " Green plants"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74647,
    "questionText": " Who firstly demonstrated experimentally the existence of electromagnetic wave?",
    "answerText": " Hertz"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74648,
    "questionText": " Which committee was assigned to recommend reforms in the insurance sector?",
    "answerText": " Malhotra Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74649,
    "questionText": " The ratio of the inertial mass to gravitational mass is equal to which number?",
    "answerText": 1
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74650,
    "questionText": " What was the first James Bond film?",
    "answerText": " Dr No"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74651,
    "questionText": " All the watches of a country are set according to which time?",
    "answerText": " Standard time of the country"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74652,
    "questionText": " During the Mughal period which trader first came to-India?",
    "answerText": " Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74653,
    "questionText": " By whom the rank of the different Ministers in the Union Council of Ministers is determined?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74654,
    "questionText": " From where does the National Stock Exchange functions?",
    "answerText": " Mumbai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74655,
    "questionText": " Which part of the pitcher plant becomes modified’ into a pitcher?",
    "answerText": " Leaf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74656,
    "questionText": " In which State is the Guru Shikhar Peak located?",
    "answerText": " Rajasthan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74657,
    "questionText": " In which region are the -most ideal conditions for the chemical weathering are found in?",
    "answerText": " Hot and humid regions"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74658,
    "questionText": " What is Electric field intensity at a point a hollow charged spherical conductor?",
    "answerText": " Is zero"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74659,
    "questionText": " Brisbane is the state capital of which SE Australian state?",
    "answerText": " Queensland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74660,
    "questionText": " Which instrument used for finding out wind-direction?",
    "answerText": " wind vane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74661,
    "questionText": " Which sound-produced by a bat?",
    "answerText": " Ultrasonic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74662,
    "questionText": " The latitude of a place is the same as which place?",
    "answerText": " Celestial pole"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74663,
    "questionText": " Which snake is not poisonus?",
    "answerText": " Pythen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74664,
    "questionText": " What is the most soluble in water?",
    "answerText": " Sugar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74665,
    "questionText": " Which geomorphic processes is associated with the work of glaciers?",
    "answerText": " Plucking"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74666,
    "questionText": " When is World Blind Day/World Sight Day observed?",
    "answerText": " 15-Oct-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74667,
    "questionText": " Which substance is more than 80% in the cell?",
    "answerText": " Water"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74668,
    "questionText": " Jallianwala Bagh massacre occurred on which date?",
    "answerText": " April 13; 1919"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74669,
    "questionText": " From which the cathode ray particles originate in a discharge tube?",
    "answerText": " Cathode"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74670,
    "questionText": " Why does north-western India receive substantial rainfall during winter months?",
    "answerText": " Westerly disturbances"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74671,
    "questionText": " Chlorophyll is a naturally occuring chelate compound in; what is the which the central metal in this?",
    "answerText": " Magnesium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74672,
    "questionText": " In which century did the famous Chinese pilgrim Fahien visit India?",
    "answerText": " 5th century AD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74673,
    "questionText": " Which is the country that has the greatest length of the day during summer?",
    "answerText": " Norway"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74674,
    "questionText": " Production of which thing is a function of liver?",
    "answerText": " Urea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74675,
    "questionText": " In which year did Annie Besant enjoy the Presidentship of the INC?",
    "answerText": 1917
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74676,
    "questionText": " Which desert is famous for its deposits of nitrates?",
    "answerText": " Atacama"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74677,
    "questionText": " If you scored cannon; which game would you be playing?",
    "answerText": " Billiards"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74678,
    "questionText": " Which of the following is used as a lubricant?",
    "answerText": " Graphite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74679,
    "questionText": " What is Maximum value of the wavelength of ultrasonic waves?",
    "answerText": " 65 cm"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74680,
    "questionText": " What is the total number of Fundamental Duties mentioned in the Constitution?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74681,
    "questionText": " What is the electorate for a Panchayat?",
    "answerText": " The Gram Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74682,
    "questionText": " When is World Intellectual Property Day; recognized by the UN is observed?",
    "answerText": " 26-Apr-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74683,
    "questionText": " Which is considered as a cell withing a cell?",
    "answerText": " Golgi appartus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74684,
    "questionText": " If we move from the equator to a pole; what will be the value of g?",
    "answerText": " Increases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74685,
    "questionText": " Which are macro-nutrients provided by inorganic fertilizers?",
    "answerText": " Nitrogen; phosphorus and potassium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74686,
    "questionText": " Which Biologist proposed the theory of Germ plasm?",
    "answerText": " Weisman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74687,
    "questionText": " Which Indian Cricketer was given the title ‘Tiger’?",
    "answerText": " Mansur Ali Khan Pataudi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74688,
    "questionText": " Mist is a result of which thing?",
    "answerText": " Condensation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74689,
    "questionText": " Which is useful in the detection of landmines?",
    "answerText": " Wasp"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74690,
    "questionText": " Who resigned as Vice-President to contest for the office of the President?",
    "answerText": " V.V. Giri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74691,
    "questionText": " Who focused his work chiefly on Sher Shah Suri?",
    "answerText": " Abbas khan Sarwani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74692,
    "questionText": " What does Oxidation involve?",
    "answerText": " Loss of electrons"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74693,
    "questionText": " What is the transfer of pollengrain from pollensac to stigma called?",
    "answerText": " Pollination"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74694,
    "questionText": " The latitude of a place expresses its angular position relative to the which place?",
    "answerText": " Equator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74695,
    "questionText": " Which river basin is called ‘Ruhr of India’?",
    "answerText": " Damodar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74696,
    "questionText": " Which substance is a bad conductor of electricity but a good conductor of heat?",
    "answerText": " Mica"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74697,
    "questionText": " Which tax is levied by the Union and collected and appropriated by the States?",
    "answerText": " Stamp Duties"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74698,
    "questionText": " The annual variability of rainfall is over 50 percent in which state?",
    "answerText": " Western Rajasthan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74699,
    "questionText": " When water is heated from degree C to 20 degree C; how does its volume change?",
    "answerText": " It shall increase"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74700,
    "questionText": " Which Indian origin immigrants became the Governor of Louisiana province of the USA in 2007?",
    "answerText": " Bobby Jindal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74701,
    "questionText": " Shiny Wilson is associated with which game/sport?",
    "answerText": " Athletics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74702,
    "questionText": " What is the distance of the nearest star besides the sun from the earth?",
    "answerText": " 4.2 light years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74703,
    "questionText": " The statements “Protoplasm is the physical basis of life” is given by which person?",
    "answerText": " Purkinje"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74704,
    "questionText": " In which region is the main area of production of icebergs found?",
    "answerText": " The West Coast of Greenland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74705,
    "questionText": " What will be the shortest day in Australia?",
    "answerText": " 21-Jun-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74706,
    "questionText": " Which two planets of the solar system have no satellites?",
    "answerText": " Mercury and Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74707,
    "questionText": " Which metal is used for making boats because it does not corrode by seawater?",
    "answerText": " Titanium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74708,
    "questionText": " Clyde Tonbaugh discovered what planet in 1930?",
    "answerText": " Pluto"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74709,
    "questionText": " In Krishnadevaraya's court; who were Ashtadiggajas?",
    "answerText": " Eight great poets of his court"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74710,
    "questionText": " What was the language of the Satavahana inscription?",
    "answerText": " Prakrit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74711,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the book colours of the rainbow?",
    "answerText": " Ranjita Biswas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74712,
    "questionText": " Why is Mohenjodaro is also known?",
    "answerText": " Mound of the Dead"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74713,
    "questionText": " Teesta forms a part of which major river system?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74714,
    "questionText": " How much of earth surface is covered by the forests?",
    "answerText": " 30 percent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74715,
    "questionText": " Why did Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq transfer his capital from Delhi to Daulatabad?",
    "answerText": " To control South India better"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74716,
    "questionText": " Under which ministry is the National River Conservation Directorate?",
    "answerText": " Ministry of Environment and Forests"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74717,
    "questionText": " Which vitamin is necessary for blood clotting?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin K"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74718,
    "questionText": " Medicines are more effective; if they are used in which state?",
    "answerText": " Colloidal state"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74719,
    "questionText": " If you wish to visit Golconda Fort; you will have to go to which state?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74720,
    "questionText": " Which of the British Officials defeated Portuguese at Sowlley?",
    "answerText": " Thomas Best"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74721,
    "questionText": " Which Gupta king is famous for his courageous stand against the Hunas?",
    "answerText": " Skanda Gupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74722,
    "questionText": " Chanda Kochhar leads to which of the organisation?",
    "answerText": " ICICI Bank"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74723,
    "questionText": " Which Mahatma Gandhi series of currency notes issued by the RBI has “ecology” depicted on it?",
    "answerText": " Rs. 100"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74724,
    "questionText": " The Maratha power reached the zenith of its glory during which reign?",
    "answerText": " Shivaji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74725,
    "questionText": " A radio broadcast from Delhi on Monday at 7.30 p.m. it is heard at New York on which day?",
    "answerText": " The same day at 7.30 a.m."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74726,
    "questionText": " Which is the Excluding the moon the celestial object the appear brightest in the sky?",
    "answerText": " Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74727,
    "questionText": " In a food chain; how much solar energy utilized by plants?",
    "answerText": " 1 percent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74728,
    "questionText": " Microwaves are electromagnetic waves with frequency; in the range of which unit?",
    "answerText": " Giga hertz"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74729,
    "questionText": " Who directed the famous T.V. serial ‘Tandoori Nights’?",
    "answerText": " Saeed Jaffrey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74730,
    "questionText": " If saving exceeds investment; how will the national income?",
    "answerText": " Remain constant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74731,
    "questionText": " Of which country Indian Constitution closely follows the constitutional system?",
    "answerText": " UK"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74732,
    "questionText": " Which provides the largest part of the demand for loanable funds in India?",
    "answerText": " Corporate businesses"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74733,
    "questionText": " What is the meaning of 'Buddha'?",
    "answerText": " The Enlightened one"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74734,
    "questionText": " What is the plane of contact of the troposphere and stratosphere?",
    "answerText": " Tropopause"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74735,
    "questionText": " Who remarked ‘the bones of the cotton weavers are bleaching the plains of India’?",
    "answerText": " William Bentinck"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74736,
    "questionText": " After whose name was a women’s division of the Indian National Army named?",
    "answerText": " Rani Jhansi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74737,
    "questionText": " Glass is made of the mixture of which things?",
    "answerText": " Sand and silicates"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74738,
    "questionText": " Which dynasty was associated with Gandhara school of Art?",
    "answerText": " Kushans"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74739,
    "questionText": " Where was first Madarasa set up by the British in India?",
    "answerText": " Calcutta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74740,
    "questionText": " Which element is essentials for the transmission of impulses in the nerve fibre?",
    "answerText": " Calcium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74741,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of a collection of poems called Golden Threshold?",
    "answerText": " Sarojini Naidu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74742,
    "questionText": " What was the main stipulation of Government of India Act; 1935?",
    "answerText": " Complete independence guaranteed"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74743,
    "questionText": " By which ruler was Pataliputra chosen for the first time as a capital?",
    "answerText": " Udayin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74744,
    "questionText": " By whom the salary and perquisites of the Prime Minister of India are decided?",
    "answerText": " Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74745,
    "questionText": " Which causes the disease syphilis?",
    "answerText": " Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74746,
    "questionText": " Which is UN special agency and not programme?",
    "answerText": " UNDP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74747,
    "questionText": " Whose tomb is ‘Biwi Ka Maqbara’?",
    "answerText": " Aurangzeb’s wife"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74748,
    "questionText": " With which river is the Omkareshwar Project associated?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74749,
    "questionText": " Which disease is caused by bacteria and spread though faecal matter by houseflies?",
    "answerText": " Typhoid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74750,
    "questionText": " Which has the largest number of sugar mills?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74751,
    "questionText": " Right to Constitutional Remedies comes under which rights?",
    "answerText": " Fundamental Rights"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74752,
    "questionText": " Who is associated with the development of India’s Atomic Bomb?",
    "answerText": " Raja Ramanna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74753,
    "questionText": " A temperature at which both the Fahrenheit and the centigrade scales have the same value?",
    "answerText": " -40°"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74754,
    "questionText": " In which state was the Nalanda University located in India?",
    "answerText": " Bihar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74755,
    "questionText": " Which sources of Islam is associated with the teachings of Prophet Mohammad?",
    "answerText": " Quran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74756,
    "questionText": " Whose nose grew when he told a lie?",
    "answerText": " Pinocchio"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74757,
    "questionText": " Which commission recommended the decentralisation system?",
    "answerText": " Balwant Rai Mehta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74758,
    "questionText": " When was the first ‘International Non-Smoking Day’ observed all over the world?",
    "answerText": " 04.07.1988"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74759,
    "questionText": " Who first divided his empire into Iqtas during the process of civil administration?",
    "answerText": " Iltutmish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74760,
    "questionText": " When does Super conductivity result?",
    "answerText": " When matter is cooled to very low temperature"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74761,
    "questionText": " What does the power of judicial review ensure?",
    "answerText": " The constitutionality of laws"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74762,
    "questionText": " The greatest threat to organisms and biodiversity in which process?",
    "answerText": " Process of habitat loss"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74763,
    "questionText": " Which Scientists has established the ‘Phylum Annelida’?",
    "answerText": " Lamark"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74764,
    "questionText": " When did the first linguistic State of Andhra come into existence?",
    "answerText": " October 1 ; 1953"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74765,
    "questionText": " Which air pollutant affect the nervous system of man?",
    "answerText": " Lead"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74766,
    "questionText": " Which nutrients are most likely to be affected by food processing and storage?",
    "answerText": " Vitamins"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74767,
    "questionText": " Air Lingus is the national airline of which country?",
    "answerText": " Republic of Ireland or Eire"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74768,
    "questionText": " Which Land tenure systems was introduced by Lord Cornwallis?",
    "answerText": " Zamindari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74769,
    "questionText": " Who is popularly known as Nightingale of India?",
    "answerText": " Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74770,
    "questionText": " The Rajya Sabha can have a maximum strength of how many members?",
    "answerText": 250
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74771,
    "questionText": " Which element does not show variable oxidation states?",
    "answerText": " Zinc"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74772,
    "questionText": " Which pop singer was nicknamed?",
    "answerText": " The Groover from Vancouver Brian Adams"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74773,
    "questionText": " Unemployment occurs when workers move from one job to another job?",
    "answerText": " Frictional unemployment"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74774,
    "questionText": " Which gas do not considered as polluting agent of air?",
    "answerText": " CO2"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74775,
    "questionText": " Who is considered as the first national ruler of India?",
    "answerText": " Chandragupta Maurya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74776,
    "questionText": " When did World Health Organization (WHO) come into force?",
    "answerText": " 7th April; 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74777,
    "questionText": " What is the position of a planet when it is nearest to the Sun;?",
    "answerText": " Perihelion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74778,
    "questionText": " How many votes are entitled for members of the UN Economic and Social Council?",
    "answerText": " One vote"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74779,
    "questionText": " Who said; ‘Child is the father of Man’?",
    "answerText": " William Wordsworth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74780,
    "questionText": " Which three important micronutrients are essential for humans?",
    "answerText": " Copper; zinc and iodine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74781,
    "questionText": " J.R.D. Tata was the first to make a solo flight from Mumbai to Karachi; in the year?",
    "answerText": 1931
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74782,
    "questionText": " Which day is the International Human Rights Day?",
    "answerText": " December 10th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74783,
    "questionText": " Medicine for high blood pressure is obtained from which species?",
    "answerText": " Rauwolffia species"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74784,
    "questionText": " By whom was the slogan ‘Inquilab Zinda bad’ first raised?",
    "answerText": " Bhagat Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74785,
    "questionText": " What is the single greatest current threat to biodiversity?",
    "answerText": " habitat destruction"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74786,
    "questionText": " Which is the Trophy/Cups associated with the game of Hockey?",
    "answerText": " Agha Khan Cup"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74787,
    "questionText": " If the current in the core decreases; what will the strength of the magnetic field be?",
    "answerText": " Decreases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74788,
    "questionText": " Which is the official language of East African Development Bank?",
    "answerText": " French"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74789,
    "questionText": " The title of Governor-General was changed to that of Viceroy in which year?",
    "answerText": " 1858 A.D."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74790,
    "questionText": " Who com merited that Cripps Mission was a postdated cheque on a crashing bank?",
    "answerText": " Mahatma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74791,
    "questionText": " Food prepared by plant; through which is transported to different part of plant?",
    "answerText": " Phloem"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74792,
    "questionText": " Who's band was The Quarrymen?",
    "answerText": " John Lenon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74793,
    "questionText": " Which state produces maximum Soya bean?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74794,
    "questionText": " The retreating monsoon withdraws from which state?",
    "answerText": " North-west India to Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74795,
    "questionText": " In which of the Parliamentary Financial Committees is the Rajya Sabha not represented?",
    "answerText": " Estimates Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74796,
    "questionText": " What is the task of the Planning Commission?",
    "answerText": " Preparation of the plan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74797,
    "questionText": " Kuroshio is a warm ocean current which runs from which country?",
    "answerText": " Philippines to Japan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74798,
    "questionText": " Who is the first Indian woman to win an Asian Games gold in 400m run?",
    "answerText": " Kamaljit Sandhu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74799,
    "questionText": " Nalanda University flourished during the reign of which ruler?",
    "answerText": " Harsha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74800,
    "questionText": " As per latest data in urban areas women employment is highest in which industry areas?",
    "answerText": " Retail Trade"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74801,
    "questionText": " Who was the President of the First Buddhist Council held at Rajagriha?",
    "answerText": " Mahakassapa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74802,
    "questionText": " Dhyan Chand’s name is associated with which game?",
    "answerText": " Badminton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74803,
    "questionText": " What is the principal structural elements of a living cell?",
    "answerText": " Carbon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74804,
    "questionText": " Which ruler of southern India were the contemporaries of kings of the Gupta empire?",
    "answerText": " Vakatakas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74805,
    "questionText": " What is the name by which Ashoka is generally referred to in his inscriptions?",
    "answerText": " Priyadarsi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74806,
    "questionText": " By whom was Neutron discovered?",
    "answerText": " Chadwick"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74807,
    "questionText": " Which fertilizer has more nitrogen content?",
    "answerText": " Urea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74808,
    "questionText": " Which element is with the highest electrical conductivity?",
    "answerText": " Silver"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74809,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the book “Termites in the Trading system”?",
    "answerText": " Jagdish Bhagwati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74810,
    "questionText": " In which Tyndall effect is not observed?",
    "answerText": " Sugar solution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74811,
    "questionText": " What is the minimum age for being the member of the Parliament?",
    "answerText": " 25 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74812,
    "questionText": " Which popular Sufi Silsilah tried to counteract the liberal religious policy of Akbar?",
    "answerText": " Naqshbandi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74813,
    "questionText": " In which veda does the word 'gotra' first appear with the meaning of 'a clan'?",
    "answerText": " Atharva Veda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74814,
    "questionText": " Which Harappan site had a dock?",
    "answerText": " Lothal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74815,
    "questionText": " Which part of human brain is the regulating centre for swallowing and vomating?",
    "answerText": " Medulla oblangata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74816,
    "questionText": " A metal plate with a circular hole at the centre is heated. What will happen to the area of the hole?",
    "answerText": " Decrease"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74817,
    "questionText": " Which remains constant while throwing a ball upward?",
    "answerText": " Acceleration"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74818,
    "questionText": " The most famous musician at the court of Akbar was Tansen; what was his original name?",
    "answerText": " Ramtanu Pande"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74819,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest planet in the solar system?",
    "answerText": " Jupiter"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74820,
    "questionText": " In which year was the Third Battle of Panipat fought?",
    "answerText": 1761
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74821,
    "questionText": " Wisdom teeth normally grow during the which age?",
    "answerText": " 17-30 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74822,
    "questionText": " Which branch of biology in which we-study about cultivation of flowering plant?",
    "answerText": " Floriculture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74823,
    "questionText": " Which major component is used in preparation of different types of glasses?",
    "answerText": " Silica"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74824,
    "questionText": " Who was an Indian King contemporary of Alexander; the Great?",
    "answerText": " Chandragupt Maurya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74825,
    "questionText": " The United Nations declared 2014 as the International Year of which thing?",
    "answerText": " Crystallography"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74826,
    "questionText": " Which state has the maximum length of surface roads?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74827,
    "questionText": " Which first woman to become a Chief Minister of any State in India?",
    "answerText": " Sucheta Kripalani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74828,
    "questionText": " Pope John Paul II played for the Polish national team what sport?",
    "answerText": " Rugby"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74829,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Asian to have received the Nobel Prize?",
    "answerText": " R.N. Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74830,
    "questionText": " In which year was the Harappan Civilization discovered?",
    "answerText": 1921
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74831,
    "questionText": " In which city of India; the diurnal range of temperature is maximum?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74832,
    "questionText": " For pasteurisation of milk by Flash method; at which temperature is milk heated?",
    "answerText": " 100°C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74833,
    "questionText": " By whom is Recognition to a political party accorded?",
    "answerText": " By the Election Commission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74834,
    "questionText": " Which compound gives both ninhydrin test and Molisch’s test?",
    "answerText": " A protein"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74835,
    "questionText": " Who decides about the reasonableness of the restrictions placed on Fundamental Rights?",
    "answerText": " Courts"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74836,
    "questionText": " In which Aryans first settled?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74837,
    "questionText": " Which is the ‘Slack Season’ in the Indian Economy?",
    "answerText": " Jan.-June"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74838,
    "questionText": " Myxoedema is disorder produed due to hyper secretion of which gland?",
    "answerText": " Thyroid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74839,
    "questionText": " What calculating aid was invented by William Oughtred in 1662?",
    "answerText": " Slide Rule"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74840,
    "questionText": " In which language was the ‘Shrimad Bhagavad Gita’ originally written?",
    "answerText": " Sanskrit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74841,
    "questionText": " With whose assistance was Bokaro Steel Limited established?",
    "answerText": " Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74842,
    "questionText": " Which House is better placed with regard to control over the executive?",
    "answerText": " Lok Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74843,
    "questionText": " Which is a true example of Median mass?",
    "answerText": " Indo-Gangetic plain"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74844,
    "questionText": " The Qutub Minar was completed by which famous rule?",
    "answerText": " Iltutmish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74845,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the book ‘Nice Guys Finish Second’?",
    "answerText": " Michael Hammer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74846,
    "questionText": " 'Who among the following are credited to have built the famous Ellora caves?",
    "answerText": " Rashtrakutas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74847,
    "questionText": " De Witt Wallace founded what?",
    "answerText": " Readers Digest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74848,
    "questionText": " Which animal belongs to the family in which Panda belongs?",
    "answerText": " Bear"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74849,
    "questionText": " Who were the first kings to issue gold coins in India?",
    "answerText": " Indo-Greeks"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74850,
    "questionText": " Which crops requires a cool growing season and a bright sun shine at the time of ripening?",
    "answerText": " Wheat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74851,
    "questionText": " Who does a liquid drop tend to assume a spherical shape?",
    "answerText": " Surface tension"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74852,
    "questionText": " What is a biotic component of ecosystem?",
    "answerText": " Water"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74853,
    "questionText": " What is the transmission of characters from one generation to next?",
    "answerText": " Heredity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74854,
    "questionText": " What wood was the cross supposed to be made of?",
    "answerText": " Mistletoe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74855,
    "questionText": " If the mass of the pendulum is doubled; what will its the time period?",
    "answerText": " Remains same"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74856,
    "questionText": " From where Alauddin Khalji captured the Delhi throne after securing fabulous wealth?",
    "answerText": " Devagiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74857,
    "questionText": " Deficiency of which vitamin causes knock-knee; bow legs and pigeon chest in children?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin D"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74858,
    "questionText": " How many players are there on each side in a women’s Basketball game?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74859,
    "questionText": " In human body which is the largest in size?",
    "answerText": " Liver"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74860,
    "questionText": " On which tax is the minimum effect of Direct Taxes?",
    "answerText": " Income"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74861,
    "questionText": " Who was the Constitutional adviser to the Constituent Assembly of India?",
    "answerText": " Dr. B. N. Rao"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74862,
    "questionText": " What is Lunar Sea?",
    "answerText": " A dark plain on the moon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74863,
    "questionText": " Who was called Zinda Pir (living saint) in Mughal India?",
    "answerText": " Aurangzeb"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74864,
    "questionText": " Which Harappan site is showing evidence of two cultural phases; Harappan and pre-Harappan;?",
    "answerText": " Chanhu-daro"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74865,
    "questionText": " By which temple is an example of the Nagara style of architecture provided?",
    "answerText": " Brihadeshwara Temple; Thanjavur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74866,
    "questionText": " During which five year plan were the steel plants at Durgapur; Bhilai and Rourkela established?",
    "answerText": " Second Five Year Plan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74867,
    "questionText": " Which animal have no blood but they respire?",
    "answerText": " Hydra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74868,
    "questionText": " A V-shaped valley is a feature produced by which river?",
    "answerText": " Youthful river"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74869,
    "questionText": " What is Super Nova?",
    "answerText": " A dying star"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74870,
    "questionText": " By whom were Sakas were finally overthrown?",
    "answerText": " Gautamiputra Satakarni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74871,
    "questionText": " Where is Indian Army’s counter-insurgency school situated?",
    "answerText": " Vairengte"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74872,
    "questionText": " Which law of thermodynamics introduces the concept of entropy?",
    "answerText": " Second law"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74873,
    "questionText": " What is the minimum permissible age for employment in any factory or mine?",
    "answerText": " 14 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74874,
    "questionText": " About 50% of the world population is concentrated between the latitudes of which degrees?",
    "answerText": " 20°N and 40°N"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74875,
    "questionText": " Which type of isomerism is shown by diethyl ether and methyl propyl ether?",
    "answerText": " Metamerism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74876,
    "questionText": " The quality of sound produced by an instrument depends on the which thing?",
    "answerText": " Number of overtones"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74877,
    "questionText": " Who was the first to land on moon?",
    "answerText": " Neil Armstrong"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74878,
    "questionText": " By whom was the absolute value of charge on electron determined?",
    "answerText": " R.A. Millikan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74879,
    "questionText": " Murrah is a breed of which animal?",
    "answerText": " Buffalo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74880,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Muslim ruler in India?",
    "answerText": " Muhammad Ghori"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74881,
    "questionText": " Which is the brightest planet?",
    "answerText": " Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74882,
    "questionText": " In organic compound; halogens are estimated by which method?",
    "answerText": " Carius method"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74883,
    "questionText": " Tansen; the greatest musician of Akbar’s court; belonged to which place?",
    "answerText": " Gwalior"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74884,
    "questionText": " N2O is more commonly known as what?",
    "answerText": " Laughing gas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74885,
    "questionText": " What is the second most abundant element in the earth’s crust?",
    "answerText": " Silicon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74886,
    "questionText": " What is the chemical formula for water glass?",
    "answerText": " Na2 SiO3"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74887,
    "questionText": " Which of Indian bird has been included in the world conservation list?",
    "answerText": " Vulture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74888,
    "questionText": " The absorption of radio waves by the atmosphere depends on which thing?",
    "answerText": " Their frequency"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74889,
    "questionText": " Which Peshwas was popularly known as Nana-Saheb?",
    "answerText": " Balaji Baji Rao"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74890,
    "questionText": " In which field ‘Aachan Maharaj’ has distinguished himself?",
    "answerText": " Dance"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74891,
    "questionText": " Nicolo Conti; the traveller; who visited Vijayanagara kingdom in 1420 A.D.; belongs to which country?",
    "answerText": " Italy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74892,
    "questionText": " Who built Char Minar?",
    "answerText": " Quli Qutb Shah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74893,
    "questionText": " Plants which lack true roots; stems and leaves are called by which name?",
    "answerText": " Thallophytes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74894,
    "questionText": " What was the first discourse of Buddha at Deer Park in Sarnath called?",
    "answerText": " Dharmachakrapravartan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74895,
    "questionText": " Which is the shortest air-route from Perth to London?",
    "answerText": " Perth; Aden; Paris; London"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74896,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the book ‘The Rights of Man’?",
    "answerText": " Thomas Paine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74897,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘Lady with Lamp’?",
    "answerText": " Florence Nightingale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74898,
    "questionText": " Why is the Gross National Income always more than Net National Income?",
    "answerText": " Direct taxes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74899,
    "questionText": " What is the Number of water molecules present in Mohr’s salt?",
    "answerText": 8
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74900,
    "questionText": " Which European country borders Atlanic Ocean?",
    "answerText": " Portugal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74901,
    "questionText": " On which principle does Rocket work?",
    "answerText": " Conservation of momentum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74902,
    "questionText": " Where are the wet hill forest found in?",
    "answerText": " Nilgiris"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74903,
    "questionText": " The famous book’ The Daughter of the East’ is written by which woman?",
    "answerText": " Ms. Benazir Bhutto"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74904,
    "questionText": " Denatured spirit is a mixture of ethyl alcohol; methyl alcohol and which other thing?",
    "answerText": " Pyridine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74905,
    "questionText": " What is the number of principal organs of UNO?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74906,
    "questionText": " Which Rashtrakuta king founded the capital city' of Manyakheta?",
    "answerText": " Dantidurga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74907,
    "questionText": " Who was the last of the 24th Jain Tirthankaras?",
    "answerText": " Mahavira"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74908,
    "questionText": " Nitrogen fixing bacteria is useful in growing which crop?",
    "answerText": " Legume"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74909,
    "questionText": " The term ‘Tee’ is connected with which game?",
    "answerText": " Golf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74910,
    "questionText": " On which planet of the solar system does the sun rise in the west and set in the east?",
    "answerText": " Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74911,
    "questionText": " Major part of CO2 is transported to respiratory surface in form of which ion?",
    "answerText": " HCO3 ion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74912,
    "questionText": " Which land mark in medical history was the first to take place?",
    "answerText": " Plastic surgery"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74913,
    "questionText": " The time at Cairo is hours ahead of Greenwich. Hence; where is it located?",
    "answerText": " 30° E longitude"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74914,
    "questionText": " NASA’s Deep Impact space mission was employed to take detailed pictures of which comet nucleus?",
    "answerText": " Tempel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74915,
    "questionText": " Ban-Ki-Moon the Secretary general of UNO belongs to which country?",
    "answerText": " South Korea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74916,
    "questionText": " The World Consumer Day is being observed on which date?",
    "answerText": " 15th March"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74917,
    "questionText": " By which act was the office of Governor General of India created?",
    "answerText": " Government of India Act; 1858"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74918,
    "questionText": " What does M3 include?",
    "answerText": " M1 + T.D"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74919,
    "questionText": " What is the most abundant metal in the earth’s crust?",
    "answerText": " Aluminium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74920,
    "questionText": " Which ruler had granted Diwani to the East India company?",
    "answerText": " Shah Alam II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74921,
    "questionText": " Which can impose reasonable restrictions on the Fundamental Rights of the Indian citizens?",
    "answerText": " Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74922,
    "questionText": " The largest coal reserves of India are found in which state?",
    "answerText": " Jharkhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74923,
    "questionText": " When it is nine o’clock in London; it will be the same time in which country?",
    "answerText": " Ghana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74924,
    "questionText": " Which environment leads to the occurrence of acid rain?",
    "answerText": " Sulphur dioxide"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74925,
    "questionText": " In which text are the original teachings of Mahavira contained?",
    "answerText": " 14 Purvas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74926,
    "questionText": " By which instrument the rate of growth of plant is measured?",
    "answerText": " Auxanometer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74927,
    "questionText": " Which proclamation of National Emergency automatically suspends?",
    "answerText": " Right to freedom"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74928,
    "questionText": " Kanchi was the capital of which rulers?",
    "answerText": " Pallavas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74929,
    "questionText": " In Homo sapiens; where does fertilisation occurs?",
    "answerText": " Oviduct"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74930,
    "questionText": " Who appointed Ibn Batuta as the Chief Qazi of Delhi?",
    "answerText": " Mohammad-bin-Tughlaq"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74931,
    "questionText": " What do you understand by the word regur?",
    "answerText": " Black soil found in the Deccan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74932,
    "questionText": " Up to how much age can the Members of the Union Public Service Commission function?",
    "answerText": " 65 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74933,
    "questionText": " Which are the high-temperature superconductors?",
    "answerText": " Ceramic oxides"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74934,
    "questionText": " Why is a water tank appears shallower when it is viewed from top?",
    "answerText": " Due to Refraction"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74935,
    "questionText": " Which is called a ‘banker’s cheque’?",
    "answerText": " Demand draft"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74936,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest river in the world?",
    "answerText": " Amazon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74937,
    "questionText": " Which was the only President of India who elected unopposed?",
    "answerText": " Neelam Sanjiva Reddy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74938,
    "questionText": " Critical criteria for the location of an aluminium plant in India are the availability of which things?",
    "answerText": " Bauxite and electricity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74939,
    "questionText": " Which type of microorganism is most widely used in industries?",
    "answerText": " Bacteria; microalgae and fungi."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74940,
    "questionText": " What is responsible for blue body syndrome?",
    "answerText": " Nitrate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74941,
    "questionText": " Which decisive battle was fought during the Third Carnatic War between the English and the French?",
    "answerText": " Wandiwash"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74942,
    "questionText": " When was the Indus Valley Civilization flourished?",
    "answerText": " During 2500-1750 B.C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74943,
    "questionText": " In which product has Bangladesh emerged as the main competitor of India in the world market?",
    "answerText": " Jute"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74944,
    "questionText": " What are Carbon; diamond and graphite together called?",
    "answerText": " Allotropes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74945,
    "questionText": " Which group of plant produce naked seed?",
    "answerText": " Gymnosperm"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74946,
    "questionText": " International voluntary blood donation day is observed on which date?",
    "answerText": " 6-Nov-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74947,
    "questionText": " Who transferred his capital from Rajgir to Pataliputra?",
    "answerText": " Udayin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74948,
    "questionText": " Barack Obama; the President of America; comes from which American States?",
    "answerText": " Illinois"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74949,
    "questionText": " By whom was the antibiotic penicillin first discovered?",
    "answerText": " Alexzander Fleming"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74950,
    "questionText": " Which technique can be used to establish the paternity of a child?",
    "answerText": " DNA finger printing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74951,
    "questionText": " What is the length of India’s coastline?",
    "answerText": " About 7500 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74952,
    "questionText": " Trees with hardwood and dense canopy are generally found in which forests?",
    "answerText": " Evergreen forests"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74953,
    "questionText": " Yamini Krishnamurti is an accomplished exponent of which dance?",
    "answerText": " Bharatnatyam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74954,
    "questionText": " Which is the compound in that oxygen shows + oxidation state?",
    "answerText": " F2O"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74955,
    "questionText": " How long are professional Golf Tour players allotted per short?",
    "answerText": " 45 seconds"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74956,
    "questionText": " Which region did not form the part of Ashoka's empire?",
    "answerText": " Madras"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74957,
    "questionText": " Which alloys is used for making magnets?",
    "answerText": " Alnico"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74958,
    "questionText": " Which noble gas was discovered in chromosphere of the sun?",
    "answerText": " Helium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74959,
    "questionText": " By whom was the Asiatic Society established in Calcutta?",
    "answerText": " Sir William Jones"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74960,
    "questionText": " Which law directly explains the law of conservation of mass?",
    "answerText": " Avogadro’s law"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74961,
    "questionText": " Pravin Arnre and Vinod Kambli played for which province in South Africa?",
    "answerText": " Boland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74962,
    "questionText": " In a sitar wire which type of vibration is produced?",
    "answerText": " Stationary transverse"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74963,
    "questionText": " There is no net transfer of energy by the particles of the medium in which waves?",
    "answerText": " Stationary waves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74964,
    "questionText": " Which is an example of Midlatitude desert?",
    "answerText": " Patagonia desert"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74965,
    "questionText": " Which State has the largest coastline in India?",
    "answerText": " Gujarat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74966,
    "questionText": " The fragments of which comet system collided with Jupiter in July 1994?",
    "answerText": " Shoemaker-Levy 9"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74967,
    "questionText": " What is the loss of water in the form of water drops called?",
    "answerText": " Guttation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74968,
    "questionText": " Which of light are strongly absorbed by plants?",
    "answerText": " Blue and red"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74969,
    "questionText": " Mount Everest; the highest peak in the world; is located in which country?",
    "answerText": " Nepal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74970,
    "questionText": " മെഥനോയിക് ആസിഡ്? ",
    "answerText": " ഫോർമിക് ആസിഡ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74971,
    "questionText": " From where do the strongest evidence that comets are members of our solar system come?",
    "answerText": " Their composition"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74972,
    "questionText": " Which was the lowest unit of Chola administration?",
    "answerText": " Valanadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74973,
    "questionText": " What are Alpha rays emitted from a radioactive substance?",
    "answerText": " Helium nuclear"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74974,
    "questionText": " Which is the only Union Territory that has a High Court of its own?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74975,
    "questionText": " If a ship moves from freshwater into seawater; what will happen?",
    "answerText": " It will rise a little higher"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74976,
    "questionText": " What do the surface of Earth that lies between the Tropic of Cancer and the Tropic; of Capricorn?",
    "answerText": " Torrid Zone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74977,
    "questionText": " What is a baby whale called?",
    "answerText": " Calf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74978,
    "questionText": " What is the situation with increasing unemployment and inflation termed?",
    "answerText": " Stagflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74979,
    "questionText": " What is the process that result in the breakdown of rocks and minerals in situ?",
    "answerText": " Weathering"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74980,
    "questionText": " How is the censorship of the press judged?",
    "answerText": " By the test of reasonableness"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74981,
    "questionText": " What is the inflation experienced in the country at present?",
    "answerText": " Cost-push inflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74982,
    "questionText": " What is the best conductor of electricity a M solution?",
    "answerText": " Sulphuric acid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74983,
    "questionText": " In which animal; is skin a respiratory organ?",
    "answerText": " Frog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74984,
    "questionText": " Which set of types actions occur in arid topography?",
    "answerText": " Attrition; Corrosion; Abrasion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74985,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest southernmost single island in India?",
    "answerText": " Great Nicobar Island"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74986,
    "questionText": " Which branch of biology deals with study of heredity and variation?",
    "answerText": " Genetics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74987,
    "questionText": " Which is not a plantation crop?",
    "answerText": " Sugarcane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74988,
    "questionText": " Amnesty International is an organisation associated with which field?",
    "answerText": " Protection of human rights"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74989,
    "questionText": " By which monk was Ashoka much influenced?",
    "answerText": " Upagupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74990,
    "questionText": " First Automatic Telephone exchange in Simla was opened at?",
    "answerText": 1913
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74991,
    "questionText": " Who started the newspaper called the “Voice of India”?",
    "answerText": " Dababhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74992,
    "questionText": " Which layer of the atmosphere provides ideal conditions for flying of jet aeroplanes?",
    "answerText": " Stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74993,
    "questionText": " Who destroyed the group of Forty Nobles?",
    "answerText": " Balban"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74994,
    "questionText": " Who used the phrase ‘Un-British’ to criticize the English colonial control of India?",
    "answerText": " Dadabhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74995,
    "questionText": " By whom was the Civil Disobedience Movement led in the North-West Frontier Province?",
    "answerText": " Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74996,
    "questionText": " What was the crux of early Buddhism?",
    "answerText": " Renunciation of desire"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74997,
    "questionText": " National animal of India?",
    "answerText": " TIGER"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74998,
    "questionText": " Famous GOLF player Vijay Singh is from which country?",
    "answerText": " Fiji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 74999,
    "questionText": " Which Place experiences minimum and maximum temperature?",
    "answerText": " 3°C and 15°C respectively is Leh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 75000,
    "questionText": " ക്ഷയരോഗത്തിന് എതിരെ നൽകുന്ന വാക്സിനാണ്? ",
    "answerText": " ബി.സി.ജി "
  }
]